<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A discourse of Christ's Second Coming and purging of his kingdom in two sermons on Matth. XIII, 41 / by Samuel Tomlyns.</title>
            <author>Tomlyns, Samuel, 1632 or 3-1700.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1695</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 153 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 53 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A62905</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing T1858</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R25655</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">09053802</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 09053802</idno>
            <idno type="VID">42338</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A62905)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 42338)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1296:19)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A discourse of Christ's Second Coming and purging of his kingdom in two sermons on Matth. XIII, 41 / by Samuel Tomlyns.</title>
                  <author>Tomlyns, Samuel, 1632 or 3-1700.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>ii, 99 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Tho. Parkhurst,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1695.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bible. --  N.T. --  Matthew XIII, 41 --  Sermons.</term>
               <term>Second Advent --  Sermons.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-11</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-11</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-12</date>
            <label>Jayanthi Reddy</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-12</date>
            <label>Jayanthi Reddy</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:42338:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A DISCOURSE OF <hi>Chriſt's Second Coming,</hi> AND The Purging of his Kingdom. In Two SERMONS on</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>Matth. <hi>xiii. 41.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>Th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Son of Man ſhall ſend forth his Angels, and ſhall gather out of his Kingdom all things that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ffe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d, and them that work Iniqui<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>y.</p>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>By SAM<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>EL TOMLYNS,</hi> A. M. Preacher of the Goſpel at <hi>Marlebo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rough.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>Tho. Parkhurſt</hi> at the <hi>Bible and Three Crowns</hi> in <hi>Cheapſide,</hi> near <hi>Mercer's Chapel,</hi> 1695.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:42338:2"/>
            <pb n="i" facs="tcp:42338:2"/>
            <head>FOR MY Much Honoured Friend Sir <hi>William Aſhurſt,</hi> Knight; Alderman of the City of <hi>LONDON.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>YOU were lately ſo ſignally Inſtrumental in Reform<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Manners of the City of <hi>London</hi> in your late Mayoralty, that I have thought it proper to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicate to you this ſmall Treatiſe concerning <hi>Chriſt's pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging and cleanſing his Kingdom from all ſcandalous Perſons and Workers of Iniquity.</hi> It is a great Reproach to Chriſtianity that ſo many pretend to it, that enervate in Principles, contradict and ſubvert its great Deſigns. How uncomely is it to be Clay Members, under a Golden Head; for carnal Creatures to claim Relation to a ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual and heavenly King? God promiſes to lay all <hi>Sion</hi>'s Borders with pleaſant Stones, <hi>Iſa. 54.12. Sanctius</hi> in his Commentary conceives, the Holy Ghoſt alludes to thoſe Stones that did divide and diſtinguiſh one Man's Land from another, in a common Field: And ſo this great Truth it taught by this Promiſe, That the Church and its true and genuine Children ſhould be diſtinguiſhed from the reſt of the world, not by ordinary and common things, but by pleaſant and precious Stones. It is the precious and ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving Knowledge of God in Chriſt, precious Faith in him, a precious Divine Nature received from him, that puts a
<pb n="ii" facs="tcp:42338:3"/>difference between the Church and the World. Notin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> and Speculative Knowledge, a cold and barren Profeſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>es, a Form of Godlineſs, a Name to live, a Lamp of Pr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, are low and mean things to diſtinguiſh between t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Church and the World. The Lord Jeſus Chriſt will <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="4 letters">
                  <desc>••••</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly appear, and ſit on the Throne of his Glory: it <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> then brand Perſons with eternal Infamy and Ignominy, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> be diſowned as no Members, to be diſclaimed as no S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects of Jeſus Chriſt, to be plucked up as Tares; to be <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> away as droſs, caſt away as bad Fiſh, and winnowed any as Chaff, to be found ſuch as have lied to Jeſus Chri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> and have woefully cheated and deceived their own S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap> It concerns us therefore to look well to it, that we experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence the Fellowſhip of Chriſt's Sufferings, and know <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> power of his Reſurrection, <hi>Phil. 3.10.</hi> Theſe are <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portant and moſt neceſſary things, to have our Luſts killed, and our Souls quickned;
<note place="margin">Rom. 6.5, 6. Col. 3.1. Rom. 6.13. 1 Pet. 2.24.</note> to have our Old Man nailed to the Croſs of Chriſt, the the Body of Sin may be deſtroy'd, that a may no more ſerve Sin, and to be pl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>d in the likeneſs of Chriſt's Reſurrection<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, ſo that we riſe with him, yield our ſelve to God as thoſe that are alive from the dead, live <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> Righteouſneſs, and ſeek the things that are above; ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Chriſt will recognize us as his Members, and acknowledge us as his Subjects, and we ſhall not be turned out of the Houſe of God, but ſtay and abide in it for ever, and when others burn with the Tares in the Furnace, we ſeal ſhine forth as the Sun in the Kingdom of our Father. If this ſmall Treatiſe may contribute any thing to your ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual Good, and eternal Salvation, it will be very great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful and acceptable to</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>
                  <date>
                     <hi>June 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>th. 1695.</hi>
                  </date>
               </dateline>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Your Affectionate, And Humble Servant;</hi> Samuel Tomlyns.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:42338:3"/>
            <head>THE Purging of Chriſt's Kingdom.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>Mat. xiii. 41.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>The Son of Man ſhall ſend forth his Angels, and they ſhall gather out of his kingdom all things that offend, and them that work iniquity.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>IN the words we have 1ſt. A Subject ſpoken of, and that is, <hi>The Son of man.</hi> 2dly. We have what is related and affirmed concerning this Subject, <hi>viz.</hi> That he <hi>ſhall ſend forth his Angels.</hi> 3dly For what end? <hi>Anſw.</hi> To <hi>gather out of his King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom;</hi> to Purge and Cleanſe it. Some have no Right to be in Chriſt's Kingdom; they are a Diſhonour and a Reproach to it; they lye to Jeſus Chriſt, they cheat and deceive their own Souls. 4. Who they are that ſhall be gather'd out of Chriſt's Kingdom? rooted out of his Fields? driven out of his Houſe? Anſw. <hi>All Things,</hi> or all thoſe that do <hi>offend,</hi> and <hi>them that work iniquity.</hi> They are <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>meer Stumblingblocks:</hi> They of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend, grieve and trouble thoſe that are in Chriſt's Kingdom; they prejudice thoſe that are without; poſſeſs their Minds with hard and bad thoughts of Chriſt's Kingdom, and ſo hinder them from entering into it, from
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:42338:4"/>embracing the Chriſtian Religion, and from ſubjecting themſelves to Chriſt's Yoke <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> Government: And all they that work <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity, and ſo ſerve Chriſt's Enemies, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> undoe and deſtroy their own Souls.</p>
            <p>The wo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> may be handled as a Doctrin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Propoſition.</p>
            <p n="1">I. Doct. <hi>The Son of Man ſhall ſend fo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> his Angels, and they ſhall gather out of his K<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom all things that offend, and them that w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> iniquity.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. I ſhall conſider the Subject ſpoken <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>the Son of Man.</hi> Who is meant by the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>of Man? Anſw.</hi> Jeſus Chriſt: He that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> called the <hi>Son of God,</hi> Joh. 9.35. Doſt th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> believe on the Son of God? Yea, he is ſtyle <hi>the only begotten Son,</hi> Joh. 3.16. &amp; Joh. 1.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>. God hath many Adopted Sons: Many S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> are led to Glory by the Captain of Salvati<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Heb.</hi> 2.17. But God hath but one begott<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> Son: He is therefore, by way of Emph<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> and Excellency, call'd his <hi>own Son:</hi> Rom. 5.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>. <hi>God ſpared not his own Son, but gave him <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> to the Death.</hi> This Son of God, in the T<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> is named the Son of <hi>Man:</hi> He that was <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> Son of God from Eternity, became the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> of Man in time: He that was the Bright<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> of his Father's Glory, was veiled and clou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> with a Humane Nature: This was as co<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> Sackcloth, and as a Dark-Lanthorn ab<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> the Son of Righteouſneſs: He that made <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> things, was made Fleſh, 1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 1.2.4.
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:42338:4"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e that was the Creator, debaſed himſelf and ſtooped to become a Creature. Which was more than if the Ocean had been leſſen'd <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o a Drop, or the Sun had joined a petty or <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>im Lamp to it ſelf; or the greateſt Emperor <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n the World had been made a Worm, to be ruſh'd and bruiſed, to redeem Worms from Deſtruction. He that was the Head of An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>els, lay under the Feet of Sinners.</p>
            <p>This Title, <hi>The Son of Man,</hi> deſerves fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>her to be conſidered. For, 1ſt. It ſeems <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> look back on the Old Teſtament, and to be borrow'd from <hi>Dan.</hi> 7.13. <hi>I ſaw in the night <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>iſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ns, and behold one like the Son of Man <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ame with the clouds of heaven, and was brought <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> before the ancient of days.</hi> This is a Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hecy of Chriſt's glorious Exaltation and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſcenſion into Heaven: The Father then <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>noured him, and ſaid, <hi>Sit thou on my right<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nd, till I make thy foes thy foot-ſtool,</hi> Pſ. 110.1. The New Teſtament explains the Old Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and the old Teſtament confirms the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ew. <hi>Daniel</hi> propheſied of the Coming of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> Son of Man, and the New Teſtament <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>lares Chriſt to be that Son of Man that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s foretold to come into the World<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly. Chriſt is ſtyled the <hi>Son of Man,</hi> with <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>pect to what he was to doe, in Purging Church, and Judging the World. The raſe here points at the great Exaltation of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>iſt, and the Glory put on Him. <hi>The of Man ſhould ſend forth his Angels, and
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:42338:5"/>they ſhall gather out of his kingdom all <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> offend, and work iniquity.</hi> This is a g<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> and glorious Work, to purge and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> his Kingdom, to put away Droſs, to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> up Weeds, to baniſh the Workers of In<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap> out of his Kingdom, to confine them to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> proper place, and caſt them into the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> nace, and ſhut them up in the Priſon. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> evidences that Chriſt hath a higher <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> than a Humane Nature; and that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> doing of this great Work, he will p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour and Glory on the Humane Na<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> which he was humbled and abaſed. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> hath appointed a Day to Judge the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> by the Man that he hath <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Act.</hi> 17.31. and hath given Chriſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity to execute Judgment, becauſe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> Son of Man, <hi>Joh.</hi> 5.27. (that is) <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> the Son of God did ſtoop, did <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> empty and abaſe himſelf to be the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> Man, and to ſuffer and die in this <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> therefore God will put Honour on <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> mane Nature, and exalt it, to try the cenſure the Actions of Men, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> them to their Eternal Place. He <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> ſentenc'd at the Tribunal of M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> arraign the whole World before <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> ment-Seat. The Son of Man is <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> nently dignify'd, when he ſhall <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> his Angels, and by them ſhall purge<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> and cleanſe his Vineyard.</p>
            <pb n="5" facs="tcp:42338:5"/>
            <p n="2">2. I ſhall now apply my ſelf to open what is affirm'd of the Son of Man. It is ſaid, <hi>He ſhall ſend forth his Angels.</hi> 1ſt. Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve, The Angels are called <hi>Chriſt</hi>'s Angels. 2dly. The Work they are employed in, <hi>viz.</hi> To gather out of his Kingdom thoſe that have neither Right or Fitneſs to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>inue there. 3dly. The Fitneſs of the <hi>Angels</hi> to that Work.</p>
            <p n="1">1. This is Honourable to Chriſt, that the Angels are call'd the <hi>Angels of the Son of Man.</hi> Here we may obſerve, That our Humane Nature is ſo exalted in Chriſt, that it is Lord over the Angels, doth commiſſio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate, ſend forth and employ them on his Er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rands, and in his Service: 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.16. It is ſaid to be part of the Myſtery of Godlineſs that God manifeſted in the Fleſh, <hi>was ſeen of Angels.</hi> They ſaw him firſt debaſed, and made lower than themſelves; <hi>Heb.</hi> 2.7. <hi>Thou <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>aſt made him a little lower than the Angels:</hi> That He might be capable of Sufferings, and feel the Edge of God's Sword, and drink the Wine of his Wrath. This was matter of Wonder, That the Lord of Angels ſhould in the form of a Servant be ſubjected to the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>age and fury of Men. And then the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels ſaw him exalted, and lifted up by God very much above them; and this did greatly aſtoniſh them, That he entred into Heaven, Angels, Principalities and Powers being made ſubject to him, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3. <hi>ult.</hi> When he
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:42338:6"/>was but a Babe in the Manger, then the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels of God were called to pay their Homage, and perform their Adoration to him, <hi>Heb.</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>. When he brought the Firſt Begotten into <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> World, he ſaith, <hi>Let all the Angels of Ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worſhip him.</hi> And if they adored him lying in the Cradle, much more may we thir<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> they will worſhip him ſitting on the Thro<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Mat.</hi> 25.3. When the Son of Man ſhall co<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> in his glory, and all the holy Angels w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> him, then ſhall he ſit on the Throne of<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Glory. When the Son of Man ſhall thu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> on the Throne of his Glory, the Angels <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> be ready to give their Attendance, to ren<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> their Obedience, in gathering elect Me<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers to their Head, in preſenting Crimin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> to his Bar, and in executing his Sentence <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> them in theſe following Scriptures, <hi>Mat.</hi> 24.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>. <hi>Luk.</hi> 19.27. <hi>Mat.</hi> 13.42. The Angels the gather the Elect to their Kingdom, b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> Offenders before their Judge, and caſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> Tares into a Furnace of unquencheable Fi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2 I ſhall a little dwell on the Work aſen<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> to the Angels, in the Text: <hi>They ſhall g<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> Men out of Chriſt's Kingdom.</hi> 1. This is ve<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> obſervable, That thoſe whom Men-Ang<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> do gather into the Church, into the Vi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> Kingdom of Chriſt, thoſe Spirit-Ange<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſhall gather out of it. The Officers <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> Paſtors are called the <hi>Angels of the Church.</hi> The Seven Stars are ſaid to be the <hi>Angels: the Seven Churches,</hi> Rev. 1.20. So we read <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="7" facs="tcp:42338:6"/>the Angel of the Church of <hi>Epheſus, Smyrna,</hi> and <hi>Pergamos,</hi> in the 2d. of the <hi>Revelations.</hi> And what is the work of theſe Men-Angels? They gather Souls into the Church, and they bring in many Hypocrites among the Sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cere, <hi>Mat.</hi> 22.10. Chriſt's Servants go forth into the High-ways, and gather together unto the Feaſt as many as they find, both Bad and Good: ſo the Net gathers and encloſes Fiſh of all kinds, both good &amp; bad, <hi>Mat.</hi> 13.47. The Good Fiſh are the Upright, and the Bad Fiſh are thoſe that are Unſound, and meerly Nominal and Titular Chriſtians. But there ſhall be a Separation, when the Net is drawn to the ſhore; then Spirit-Angels ſhall gather theſe bad Men out of the Church, which Men-Angels did gather into it. Men may be impoſed on, and be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived, but Angels will not be cheated and deluded. What doth it advantage Hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crites, to blind the Eyes of Paſtors? They cannot caſt a Miſt before, or put a Veil on the Eyes of Angels: Thoſe that are paſſable Pieces, and current Coin among the Saints, will yee be diſcovered to be reprobate Silver, and counterfeit Coin, by the Angels: They will know thoſe that Miniſters cannot diſcern.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Good Angels will gather out of Chriſt's Kingdom, thoſe that Bad Angels do gather into it: <hi>Mat.</hi> 13.25. <hi>While men ſlept, an enemy came and ſowed tares among the wheat,
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:42338:7"/>and went his way.</hi> Who is this <hi>Enemy?</hi> Chriſt, in <hi>Mat.</hi> 13.39. tells us, it is the <hi>Devil.</hi> What are the <hi>Tares?</hi> Chriſt er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounds this of the Children of the <hi>wicked one, Mat.</hi> 13.38. The <hi>Field</hi> of Chriſt is the Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſal Viſible Church, ſpread through the World, <hi>Mat.</hi> 13.38. The ſame that is call'd the <hi>Kingdom</hi> of Chriſt in the Text, i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the <hi>World</hi> in <hi>Mat.</hi> 13.38. It is not to be un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood of the World at large, but the Cul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tivated, the Manured, the Tilled part of the World; and that is the Univerſal Viſible Church ſpread through many Nations of the World. So that it is plain from this Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, that Satan brings and ſows many of his Children in the Church: But is it <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> ſtrange, improbable, and almoſt incredible that Satan ſhould bring Men into the Church. Is not this a dangerous Place for his Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects to be in? May he not loſe them <hi>Anſw.</hi> Satan doth bring many into the Church with a deep Deſign, and for politi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> Ends. 1. Satan counts this for his Ho<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap> and Glory, to have Subjects, Servants and Children of his even <hi>in</hi> the Church, a well as <hi>without;</hi> That he has Vaſſals for <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> ſervice, among the Veſſels of Honour the are for God's uſe. As this exalts Chriſt, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> he rules among his Enemies, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 110.2 <hi>Rule thou in the midſt of thine enemies;</hi> ſo th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> advances Satan, that he alſo rules among <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> Enemies, that he can retain his Prey, kee<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="9" facs="tcp:42338:7"/>his Captive, preſerve his Subjects faſt, and cloſe to him among his Enemies, even where God and Chriſt rule, and Saints do yield obedience; That he can maintain an intereſt for himſelf, where the Light ſhines, Grace beams, the Laws of Chriſt are proclaimed, and the danger of rebelling againſt them is openly declared; That yet his Soldiers will not leave his tents, nor his Subjects caſt of his yoke, nor renounce their obedience to him. 2. Satan is content and willing that many of his Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren ſhould creep into and be joined to the Church, that they may be more ſecure; that now they may ſlatter themſelves that they are ſafe from danger, and may bleſs themſelves in the hope of a Place in God's Kingdom, and a Portion among his Sons and Daughters. How many do betake them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves to the Church, as a City of Refuge, as a Sanctuary to preſerve themſelves from Deſtruction, though they go on in their wickedneſs? God, by <hi>Jeremiah,</hi> complains, <hi>Jer.</hi> 7.12. That the proſane Jews did uſe the Temple as if it were a Den of Robbers: as Robbers do ſpoil Travellers, and then retreat to their Dens, as places of ſafety and ſecurity; ſo they did ſteal, murther, commit Adultery, ſwear falſely, and then come and ſtand in the Temple, offer ſome Sacrifices, and then conclude a Compenſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion was made to God for all the wrong they had done him; that now they were de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liver'd
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:42338:8"/>liver'd from the guilt they had contracted, and ſecured from the puniſhment they had deſerved. So <hi>Auguſtine,</hi> in his 22d. <hi>lib. de Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vitate</hi> (as I remember) ſpeaks of many Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians in his time, That though they did lead lend and looſe lives, yet they thought they ſhould be ſaved at laſt, becauſe they believed the true and right Doctrine. And how many in theſe days do caſt their cold and formal Prayers, their blind and heartleſs De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>votions into the ſcale, to ballance and weigh down all their groſs and notorious Wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs. Thus is a falſe Notion of the Church and Kingdom of Chriſt, a great Means, and a myſtical Inſtrument to uphold Satan's Throne, and keep the Crown on his Head. The Name of Chriſtianity encourages many to perſiſt in the practice of Iniquity, without fear of Miſery &amp; Deſtruction. 3. Satan brings Men into the Church, that they may doe him more ſervice in the Church, than they could doe out of it. The Tares did draw away the Sap and Strength of the Earth from the good Corn, did entangle and harle about the Wheat, pull it down, keep it low, hinder its growth and flouriſhing: ſo Satan's Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren in the Church, they aſpire to, and reach after the higheſt places, they graſp the Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours and Proſits that were deſign'd for better Men, they keep the ſincere People of God low, they pull them down, and lay ſuch under them, they will hardly allow them a place
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:42338:8"/>and ſubſiſtence in the Church, they traduce and reproach them as Puritans, Praeciſians, Fanaticks, that make the Way to Heaven narrower, and the Yoke of Chriſt heavier, and the Commands of Chriſt ſtricter than indeed they are: They think they call Men to hard ſervices, and bind heavy burdens on them, when Chriſt gives larger allowances, and Men may go to Heaven without ſuch ſtrictneſs, without ſo much adoe, without keeping ſo ſtrict a rein on the fleſh, without continual curbing of their luſts, and denying their natural appetites and inclinations; and when theſe Men have advantages on their ſide, and carnal Rulers that will comply with them, they are ready to perſecute; they are forward to execute Penal Laws, and perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cute thoſe of the ſame Nation, City, Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bourhood, to the utmoſt, that they may ruine and undoe them; as in <hi>Abraham</hi>'s Family, <hi>Iſhmael</hi> perſecuted <hi>Iſaac: Gal.</hi> 4.29.30. <hi>It is now they that are born after the fleſh, perſecute thoſe that are born after the ſpirit. Calvin</hi> would ſay, That a Man need go no farther than <hi>Geneva</hi> to be perſecuted. I have heard that ſome profane Ones in that City, would, in contempt and hatred of <hi>Calvin,</hi> call their Dogs <hi>Calvin.</hi> This holy Man choſe rather to leave <hi>Geneva,</hi> and to go into voluntary exile to <hi>Strasburg</hi> in <hi>Germany,</hi> than to admit looſe and profane Men to the Table of the Lord. The Tares do much miſchief to the
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:42338:9"/>good Corn, and much ſervice to Satan, by being in the ſame Field, the ſame Church with the ſincere and upright Servants of Chriſt.</p>
            <p>But thoſe that Satan hath thus, and for theſe Ends introduced into the Church, vail<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing their Enmity againſt Chriſt, and his People, under the name of Chriſtianity; theſe the Good Angels will ſeparate and ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther out of the Church, that they may ſuffer for mocking of Chriſt, for hating and hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dering his People.</p>
            <p n="3">3dly. Let us conſider how meet and fit Good Angels are for this Work to which they are deſigned, and in which they are em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployed.</p>
            <p n="1">1. They excell in Judgment, Wiſdom and Underſtanding. To be Wiſe as an Angel of God, was grown to a Proverb in <hi>Iſrael,</hi> 2 Sam. 14.20. <hi>My lord the king is wiſe as as angel of God.</hi> As the Angel that deſtroy'd the Egyptians Firſt-born, could obſerve and diſtinguiſh between the Iſraelites Houſes that had Blood ſprinkled at the Door of them, and the Egyptians Houſes that had no Blood ſprinkled on them, though it were in the midſt of the Night: So the Angels of God do know and will underſtand, who are ſprinkled with the Blood of Chriſt, and ſo muſt ſtay in Chriſt's Kingdom; and who are not, and ſo muſt be gathered out of Chriſt's Kingdom, and deſtroyed: They
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:42338:9"/>will diſcover thoſe that have eſcaped the Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervation of Paſtors, and have deluded them with their fair Pretences: They will be able to waſh off the Paints, and pull away the Veils of Hypocrites, and ſo will pull them out of the Kingdom of Chriſt: They know that they were not ſent forth to miniſter to the Wicked, but to the Saints, <hi>Heb.</hi> 1.14. that Hypocrites were no part of their charge; that they did not attend on them, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore can diſtinguiſh and mark them out, to be gathered out of the Kingdom of Chriſt.</p>
            <p n="2">2. The Angels do excell in Strength: <hi>Bleſs the Lord, ye his Angels, that excell in ſtrength.</hi> As <hi>Nebuchadnezzar</hi> employ'd the moſt migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty Men in his Army, <hi>Dan.</hi> 3.20. to bind <hi>Shadrach, Meſhach</hi> and <hi>Abed-nego,</hi> and to caſt them into the Fiery Furnace; ſo the Angels are the mightieſt Soldiers in God's Hoſt, the moſt valiant of his Army, and theſe he charges to reap the Tares, to bind them in bundles, and to caſt them into an Eternal Furnace, <hi>Mat.</hi> 13.30, 39, 42. The Angels are ſtrong and mighty Reapers. Can the Tares ſtand before the Hook, or withſtand the Sickle of theſe mighty Reapers? Can the Tares hinder themſelves from being bound up in bundles, and caſt into a Furnace of unquenchable Fire? Though wicked Men are many, a huge multitude, and great in power, and high in authority here in this world, yet their numbers, ſtrength or force
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:42338:10"/>cannot ſecure or protect them from theſe mighty Reapers.</p>
            <p>But who are thoſe that ſhall be <hi>gathered out of the Kingdom of Chriſt?</hi> This is for Chriſt's Glory: If the whole Church is the Kingdom of Chriſt, it is his Dominion; and this is farther for his Honour, that he will purge this Kingdom of his, that the Beauty, Purity, and Holineſs of it may appear. As Jeſus Chriſt is <hi>fairer than the Children of Men,</hi> Pſal. 45.2. So the Church is to appear as the <hi>faireſt among Women,</hi> 1 <hi>Cant.</hi> 8. The Church is ſtyled the <hi>Mountain of Holineſs,</hi> Jer. 31.23. and vaſtly differs from the Kingdoms of the World, that are called <hi>Mountains of Prey,</hi> Pſal. 76.4. That Society that is ſet forth as the Kingdom of Heaven, <hi>Mat.</hi> 25.1. and is indeed the Suburbs of Heaven, ſhould not be clogged with <hi>fooliſh Virgins,</hi> and be defiled with the Workers of Iniquity. Wicked Men and Hypocrites are called <hi>Droſs,</hi> Pſal. 119.119. <hi>Reprobate Silver,</hi> Jer. 6.30. <hi>Braſs, Tin, Iron,</hi> and <hi>Lead,</hi> Ezek. 22.18. And what doth ſuch baſe Metal do among the Veſſels of <hi>Gold</hi> and <hi>Silver?</hi> 2 Tim. 2.20. Should not Chriſt's Floor be cleanſed from <hi>Chaff?</hi> Mat. 3.12. Should not bad Fiſh be pluck'd out of the Net, and caſt away? <hi>Mat.</hi> 13.47, 48. What ſhould thoſe do in God's Houſe that are not Sons of God, <hi>John</hi> 8.35. but are Children of Satan, <hi>John</hi> 8.44. and Servants of Sin? <hi>John</hi> 8.34. What ſhould they do among
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:42338:10"/>the Gueſts at the Feaſt, that have neither Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petites, nor Wedding-Garments, <hi>Mat.</hi> 22.10, 11. Can carnal Creatures partake of ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual Bleſſings? Men are born Fleſh, <hi>John.</hi> 3.6. and ſpiritual Bleſſings are to be enjoyed in Heavenly Places, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 1.3. Can Earthly Men and Women inherit a Heavenly Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try, <hi>Hebr.</hi> 11.16. they whoſe Thoughts and Hearts dwell on Earth, <hi>Luk.</hi> 21.35. they that pant after the Duſt of the Earth, <hi>Amos</hi> 2.7. they that mind Earthly Things only, <hi>Phil.</hi> 3.19. that ſeek nothing higher, than what they ſhall eat, what they ſhall drink, wherewithal they ſhall be cloathed? <hi>Mat.</hi> 6.31, 32. Can theſe live in the pure and ſine Air of ſpiritual Comforts, Delights, and Enjoyments? Can dead Creatures converſe with the living God? Can thoſe that wear fordid and filthy Gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments preſent themſelves with acceptance before a God that is of purer Eyes than to behold Iniquity? <hi>Hab.</hi> 1.13. An Hypocrite ſhall not come before him, <hi>Job.</hi> 13.16. The Fooliſh ſhall not ſtand in his ſight: Evil ſhall not dwell with him. God hates all the Workers of Iniquity, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 5.4, 5. What ſhould profane Ones do in the Mountain of Holineſs? <hi>Jer.</hi> 31.23. What ſhould the Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>righteous do in the Habitation of Juſtice? What ſhould corrupt and ſtinking Creatures do in the Mountain of Myrrh, and in the Hill of Frankincenſe? <hi>Cant.</hi> 4.6. Such gangreen'd Members muſt be cut off from
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:42338:11"/>the Body: Such Spots muſt be waſhed away out of the Face of the Church.</p>
            <p>But more particularly, I ſhall addreſs my ſelf to conſider the Words in the Text: The <hi>Angels ſhall gather out of Chriſt's Kingdom<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d things that offend, and them that work iniquity</hi> 1. <hi>The Angels ſhall gather out</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> that is, all the Scandals, all the Stumbling blocks, all that offend others, and obſh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> their entring into the Kingdom of Ch<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> It is ſad to be in the Church only as Sun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bling-blocks to diſgrace the Faith, to reproa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> the Doctrine of Chriſt, to ſtop or cool othe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> in the way everlaſting, to turn them out o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the Paths of Holineſs, and to hurry the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> headlong to deſtruction. How do the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> Examples of ſome influence, and learn o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers! one Man's wicked Life and Do<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> infects another's: If ſome Neighbours a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> Drunkards, are Swearers, are Whoremaſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> are Lyars, are Sabbath-breakers, negl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap> Prayer in their Families, do not inſtra<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> their Children, or reſtrain their Serva<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> from Wickedneſſes; if they are Mock<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>s Religion, Scoffers at Godlineſs, and H<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> of Good Men that <hi>will not run with <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> to the ſame exceſs of Riot,</hi> 1 Pet. 4.4<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Theſe evil Precedents do eaſily and qui<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> prevail on others. It was grown to a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> verb in <hi>Iſrael,</hi> Ezek. 16.44. <hi>As is the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> ſo is her Daughter:</hi> So I may ſay, As is <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> Father, ſo are his Children; as is the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter,
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:42338:11"/>ſo are his Servants; as is the Neighbour, ſo are his Companions, and thoſe that con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſe with him. <hi>Ezek.</hi> 20.18, 21. God ſaid to the Children, <hi>Walk ye not in the ſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutes of your Fathers, neither obſerve their Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments:</hi> Yet they walked not in God's Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutes, nor obſerv'd his Judgments, but per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſted in a conformity to the evil Practices of their Parents, that were ſo powerful, that they had the force of Statutes, Judgments, and binding Laws. How hard, how rare is it to caſt off, or deſiſt from a vain Conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſation, delivered by Tradition from Fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fathers and Neighbours, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.18. How pernicious, fatal, and deſtructive, are ſuch Scandals! For 1. Such do teach others the way of Sin and Wickedneſs: <hi>Jer.</hi> 2.33. <hi>Therefore haſt thou alſo taught the wicked ones thy ways.</hi> When Chriſtians ought to <hi>teach Tranſgreſſors,</hi> Pſal. 51.13. by their Doctrines and Examples, <hi>God's ways</hi> for their <hi>Converſion,</hi> and Salvation, they teach wicked Ones their own corrupt ways for their deſtruction. 2. Such do juſtifie the Wicked of the World in all their lewd Practices: <hi>Ezek.</hi> 16.51. <hi>Thou haſt juſtified thy ſiſters in all thine abomination, which thou hast done:</hi> 46, 48. <hi>Samaria</hi> was her Siſter, and <hi>Sodom,</hi> and theſe Siſters, <hi>Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruſalem</hi> had juſtified by her Abominations O that thoſe that pretend to be Chriſt's Subjects, ſhould juſtifie his open and profeſs'd Enemies, and approve the Heathen World in all their
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:42338:12"/>Drunkenneſs, Lyings, Injuſtice, and Adul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teries! 3. Such do comfort Sinners in their ungodly Practices: <hi>Ezek.</hi> 16.54. <hi>That this mayeſt bear thine own ſhame, and mayeſt be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>founded in all that thou haſt done,</hi> in that thou art a comfort to them. If ſo be thoſe that are not of the Church, but Strangers and Enemies to it, do ſee Chriſtians roul in Fil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thineſs, and drink in Iniquity like Water, How will they be encouraged to, and comfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted in their ſinful Practiſes? Such will con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude there is no danger in their ways, or judgment towards their Perſons, but that they may ſin without fear of puniſhment, or dread of vengeance.</p>
            <p n="4">4. How great a Scandal is it, when thoſe that profeſs themſelves the People of God, and pretend to be of the Church, ſhall out goe, and outſtrip Heathens in their Wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs! <hi>Jer.</hi> 5.28. <hi>They overpaſs the deeds of the wicked;</hi> that is, of the wicked Heathen! <hi>Ezek.</hi> 5.6. <hi>She hath changed my judgments <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> wickedneſs more than the nations, and my ſtatute more than the Countries that are round about <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> Ezek. 16.48. God confirms this truth with a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Oath, <hi>As I live, ſaith the Lord God,</hi> Sodo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>thy ſiſter hath not done, ſhe nor her daughter, as thou haſt done:</hi> Ezek. 16.51. <hi>Neither <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> Samaria <hi>committed half of thy ſins.</hi> How horrible a Scandal is this, when the Heath<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> are aſhamed of, and reflect on the Sins of thoſe that call themſelves of the Church
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:42338:12"/>Ezek. 16.27. <hi>The daughters of the Philiſtines are aſhamed of thy lewd way.</hi> I have heard from one that lived at <hi>Smyrna,</hi> That the <hi>Turks</hi> will laugh, and make Tricks at the <hi>Grecian</hi> Chriſtians there, when they are drunk. Theſe blind Mahometans do diſlike and are aſhamed of Drunkenneſs.</p>
            <p n="5">5. Such Scandals, or ſcandalous Perſons, cauſe the Name of God to be profaned and blaſphemed among the Heathen: <hi>Ezek.</hi> 36.20. <hi>When they entred in to the Heathen whither they went, they profaned my holy name, when they ſaid to them, Theſe are the people of the Lord, and are gone forth out of his land;</hi> that they committed ſuch Wickedneſſes, and were for this caſt out of their Land. This cauſed the Heathen to think baſely of God, that he was like them, and did approve of their Wickedneſſes, or that he was weak, and could not preſerve his pretended People in their own Land; but the Heathen pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vailed againſt them, and led them captive: <hi>Rom.</hi> 2.23, 24. <hi>Thou that makeſt thy boaſt of the law, through breaking the law diſhonoureſt thou God? For the name of God is blaſphemed among the Gentiles through you, as it is written. Salvian</hi> tells us how much the <hi>Vandals</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flected on Chriſt's beholding the wicked Life of Chriſtians; <hi>Si Chriſtus Sancta docuiſſet, Chriſtiani Sanctè vixiſſent:</hi> That Father ſaith, The <hi>Chriſtians</hi> were Drunkards, Whore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maſters, Unjuſt; when the <hi>Vandals</hi> were
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:42338:13"/>Temperate, Chaſt, and more Juſt in their Dealings. It is ordinary, if you queſtion a <hi>Turk</hi> in his Dealings, Whether what he ſaith of the price or value of Goods be true, to break out into a Reproach of Chriſtianity thus, <hi>Doſt thou think I am a Chriſtian, and that I will lye and couzen in my dealings?</hi> How much were the <hi>Indians</hi> in the <hi>Weſt-Indies</hi> prejudiced againſt Chriſtianity, by the barbarous and cruel dealings of the <hi>Spaniards</hi> with them? An <hi>Indian</hi> asked a <hi>Spaniard,</hi> Whither the <hi>Spa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niards</hi> did go after Death? and the <hi>Spaniard</hi> anſwering that they went to Heaven: the poor <hi>Indian</hi> Heathen replied, He would not go to Heaven, to meet ſuch a cruel and bloody People there; but would rather <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> to Hell, where his Anceſtors and Fath<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> were. Yea, theſe poor Heathen Idolater juſtified themſelves, and ſaid, Their Gods were better than the <hi>Spaniard</hi>'s God: Fee the <hi>Indians</hi> worſhipped Gods of Gold and Silver; when the <hi>Spaniards</hi> worſhipped tw<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Sticks acroſs; that is, they adored a woode<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Croſs.</p>
            <p n="6">6. Theſe Scandals do foment Atheiſm, e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe and ſpread it in the World: 1. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> their teaching pernicious, and Heretical Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrines, contrary to the Truth of Chriſt, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> ſo divide Chriſtians, crumble them into lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle Parties, and Factions, cauſe them ſo to claſh and interfere one with another, to op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, decry, contradict, judge, and cenſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="21" facs="tcp:42338:13"/>each other. <hi>Grotius</hi> takes in this as part of the ſence of the Words, That there are Scandals in Doctrine,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>in</hi> Locum.</note> as well as in Manners. The Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> ſpeaks of <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>Rom.</hi> 16.17. Scandals other than the Doctrines he and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers had preach'd: <hi>Mat.</hi> 18.7. Chriſt faith, <hi>It muſt needs be that</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> Offences come: Which <hi>Paul</hi> expreſſes thus, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.19. <hi>For there muſt be alſo Hereſies among you. Gretius</hi> doth paralel theſe two Texts, and thinks they intend the ſame thing. Certain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly variety of Opinions, rotten and corrupt Doctrines, do much contribute and conduce to Atheiſm. How many reſolve only to ſtick to Morality, and juſt Dealing with Men, accounting that all Religion is but a Fable, or Fiction, becauſe Men have ſuch contrary Notions, ſuch contradictory Sentiments a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout it. 2. Scandals in Action: A lewd and wicked Life doth exceedingly advance Athe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſm. I have heard of a Woman that fell off from all Religion, and turned a profeſs'd Atheiſt; and when the Miniſter of her Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh went to diſcourſe with her, and rebuke and reprove her for her Atheiſm, ſhe ſmartly replied, That he was the cauſe of it; when ſhe heard what he preached in the Pulpit, and obſerv'd how contrary he practiſed out of it, what a looſe and wicked Life he led, ſhe was tempted to conclude that all Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion was but a Cheat, a meer politick Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trivance;
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:42338:14"/>for if he himſelf believed what he ſpake in the Pulpit to be true, he would never lead ſuch a ſcandalous and bad Life out of it, he would reſtrain himſelf from vice, and order his Converſation aright. How many would incline to Atheiſm, and think the Chriſtian Doctrine but a Fable, if it brought forth no better Fruits in the Lives of others, than theſe? And that Heave<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> were but a Fiction, if none were more fit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted and prepared for it than theſe carnal and profane Chriſtians are? How righteous and requiſite is it then, that Perſons that ſo of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend others, diſhonour God, and reproach Chriſtianity, ſhould be <hi>gathered out of the Kingdom of Chriſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2dly. Thoſe <hi>that work iniquity</hi> ſhall be pluck'd out, and for ever ſeparated from the <hi>Kingdom</hi> of Chriſt. Firſt there are ſome that pretend to be Members of the Church <hi>that do work iniquity.</hi> 2. I ſhall ſhew what a heinous Evil, what a crying Provocation it is to <hi>work iniquity</hi> in the Church; that is, the viſible <hi>Kingdom</hi> of God and Chriſt.</p>
            <p n="1">1. There are ſome that are got into the Viſible Church, and are call'd <hi>God's People,</hi> that yet work Iniquity. 1. They early be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin this Employment, <hi>Zeph.</hi> 3.7. <hi>They riſe up early, and corrupted all their doings.</hi> How croſs and contrary are Men to God? He did riſe up early, and ſend his Prophets to inſtruct them in their Duty, to diſſuade them
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:42338:14"/>from Sin, and to exhort them to Righteouſneſs; the Prophets came early in the Morning to teach the Jews in the Temple; yet all was in vain; no Damms would ſtop, no Banks would bound in the Torrent of their Sins: The Imaginations of Man's Heart are evil from his Youth, or Childhood, <hi>Jer.</hi> 3.25. <hi>We and our fathers have ſinned againſt the Lord our God, from our youth unto this day:</hi> Jer. 22.21. <hi>This hath been thy manner from thy youth, that that thou obeyedſt not my voice.</hi> 2. They do this work diligently, <hi>Mich.</hi> 7.3. They do evil with both hands earneſtly, <hi>Jer.</hi> 9.5. They weary themſelves to commit Iniquity: <hi>They drink in iniquity like water,</hi> Job 15.16. Like as a thirſty Man drinks in Water, and can hardly ſatisfie himſelf, they draw iniquity to them with cords of <hi>vanity,</hi> that is, with ſinful, corrupt, unbelieving Reaſons and Sug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſtions: thoſe indeed are falſe and very weak, and therefore may well be called Cords of Vanity; yet on wicked Men they have the force of a ſtrong Cart-rope, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 5.18, 19. They think God will not draw near to them in Judgment, or ſhew his work of Vengeance and Severity on them. 3. They only follow this work and no other: A cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupt Tree can bring forth no other but cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupt Fruit, <hi>Mat.</hi> 7.17, 18. An unclean Fountain, night and day vents no other but polluted Streams, <hi>Jer.</hi> 6.17. Satan's Mint is ſtill going in the Soul. An evil Man
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:42338:15"/>brings forth evil things out of the evil trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure of his heart, <hi>Mat.</hi> 12.35. God accuſes the Jews by <hi>Jeremiah,</hi> That that they had done nothing of all that God commanded them; That the Children of <hi>Judah</hi> had only done evil before the Lord; That the Children of <hi>Iſrael</hi> had only provoked him to anger, <hi>Jer.</hi> 32.23, 30. 4. They perſiſt, continue and go on in this work: <hi>Ezek.</hi> 23.43. <hi>I ſaid unto her that was old in adulteries, W<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> they now commit adulteries with her, and ſhe with them?</hi> Yet in <hi>ver.</hi> 44. it is ſaid, She con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued in her whoredom, and did not give off. <hi>Can the Ethiopian change his skin, or the Leopard his ſpots? then may they that are ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>customed to do evil, learn to do well,</hi> Jer. 13.2. The Hearts of Sinners are bent to backſlide, <hi>Hoſ.</hi> 11.7. They have loved Strangers, and after them they will go, <hi>Jer.</hi> 2.25. They are of their Father the Devil, and his luſts they will do, <hi>Joh.</hi> 8.44. This they are ſixed in, this they are reſolved on; and tho<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> it be the Duty of Men to receive the Law from God's Mouth, <hi>Job</hi> 22.22. yet they declare they will doe whatſoever proceeds out of their own mouth, <hi>Jer.</hi> 44.17. and ſo they oppoſe their own mouth to the mouth of God. 5. They rejoyce to doe Evil, <hi>Jer.</hi> 11.17. <hi>When thou doſt evil, then thou re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joycest.</hi> Sinners chuſe their own ways, and their Soul delights in their Abominations, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 66.3. They count it pleaſure to riot in
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:42338:15"/>the day-time, 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.13. Thus deceived Sinners imagin and conceit a Heaven in that which indeed fits them for Hell, and prepareth them for everlaſting Torments. The day is coming, when they that ſhall review all their ſenſual Delights, and draw their greateſt bitterneſs out of that which hath been moſt ſweet to them; Oh, how terrible will it be, to draw a Real Hell of Miſery out of their Imaginary and Momentary Heaven of Felicity! Their preſent Pleaſures will be a ſeed of Pain, and of eternal Torments.</p>
            <p n="2">2dly. I ſhall ſhew you what a hainous and provoking thing it is, to work Iniquity in the Kingdom of Chriſt. For, 1. They that are of the Church, they do profeſs and avow the Lord to be their God, <hi>Hoſ.</hi> 8.2. <hi>Iſrael ſhall cry unto me, My God, we know thee.</hi> Yet in <hi>ver.</hi> 3. it is ſaid, <hi>Iſrael hath cast off the thing that is good.</hi> And <hi>Aholah</hi> (ſaith God) <hi>played the harlot when ſhe was mine,</hi> Ezek. 23.5. How treacherous are they that ſay, God is their Father? <hi>Joh.</hi> 8.41. <hi>We have one Father, even God;</hi> yet they partake of Satan's cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupt Nature, bear his Image, and do his Luſts: <hi>John</hi> 8.44. <hi>Ye are of your Father the devil, and the luſts of your Father ye will do.</hi> How abominable is this, to wear God's Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very, and yet do Satan's drudgery? How doth God complain, and call Heaven and Earth to witneſs againſt <hi>Iſrael! I have nou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhed and brought up Children, yet they have
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:42338:16"/>rebelled againſt me,</hi> Iſaiah 1.2. The Heaven and the Earth, and all the Creatures, ſerve Man, yet he denies Obedience to his Maker. Thoſe that are in the Church are under more Ties and Obligations than others: <hi>Amos</hi> 3.2. <hi>You only have I known of all the families of the earth:</hi> When it is ſaid of the Gentiles, That they were a People that Chriſt did not know, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 55.5. Yet Chriſt <hi>came to his own, and his own received him <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>,</hi> John 1.11. Who ſhould welcome him, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> open their Hearts, and receive him, if not his own? Yet Chriſt's own rejected him Not only they ſhut the Door againſt hi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, but alſo poured out their Fury on him, and cut him off from the Land of the Livi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>. God complains, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 81.11. <hi>But my pe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> would not hearken to my voice: Iſrael would b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> none of me.</hi> And indeed, would be none o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> his. 2. Thoſe that are in Chriſt's <hi>Kingd<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> they are near to God, and in his ſpecial P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence; and it is therefore more heinous <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> ſuch to work <hi>Iniquity:</hi> 1. They are near <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> God, <hi>Jer.</hi> 13.2. God bids <hi>Jeremiah</hi> to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e him a Linnen Girdle, and put it on his Lo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap> and God expounds the meaning of this Sig<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>ver.</hi> 11. <hi>For as the girdle cleaveth to the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> a man; ſo have I cauſed to cleave unto me <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> whole houſe of Iſrael, that they might be <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> me for a people, and for a name, and for a pra<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e, and for a glory: but they would not hear.</hi> God ſpeaks here of <hi>Iſrael</hi> as his viſible Church:
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:42338:16"/>And by the Covenant that was between God and them, they were as a Girdle put on bound to him, and were to cleave to him, both for God's Honour and Glory. As a Girdle is an Ornament to a Man; ſo thoſe that are truly God's People are his Glory, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 46.13. <hi>I will place ſalvation in Zion, for Iſrael my Glory:</hi> 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 8.23. The Apoſtle ſpeaks of <hi>the Meſſengers of the Churches,</hi> that they were <hi>the Glory of Chriſt;</hi> ſuch Church-Members ought to be. Yet thoſe that work Iniquity in the Kingdom of Chriſt, are a Diſhonour, a Diſgrace, a Reproach to Chriſt. 2. A Girdle is put on and worn about the Loins of a Man; and this is an Honour to the Girdle it ſelf, that it is ſo near to a Man, and is worn as an Ornament by him: So God is the Glory of Men, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 60.13. <hi>Thy God ſhall be thy Glory.</hi> For Men to be brought under a Covenant with God, and by this means to be joined to God, this is the Glory of Men, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 50.5. <hi>Gather my Saints toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, that have made a Covenant with me by Sacrifice.</hi> To be God's Confederates is the Honour of Men; but <hi>thoſe that work <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>niquity</hi> in Chriſt's <hi>Kingdom,</hi> do turn this Glory into Shame. This is their Infamy, To break the Marriage-Covenant, <hi>Hoſ.</hi> 4.12. to go <hi>a whoring from under their God;</hi> to doat on Creatures, and proſtitute themſelves to Idols: Such <hi>ſhall bear the Reproach</hi> (ſaith God, <hi>Micah</hi> 6.16.) <hi>of my People:</hi> They ſhall be expoſed
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:42338:17"/>to everlaſting Infamy, for mocking of God, and lying to him, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 50.16, 17. <hi>What beſt thou to do to take my covenant into thy mouth? Seeing thou hateſt inſtruction, and caſteth my words behind thee.</hi> Though they were call<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> Saints, by reaſon of their profeſſion and co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligation to be ſuch; yet, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 50.16. they are called <hi>wicked,</hi> by reaſon of their hating <hi>Inſtruction,</hi> and caſting God's Words beh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>d their Backs. 2. Thoſe that are in Chriſts Kingdom, they are in God's ſpecial Preſence <hi>For God dwelleth in</hi> Zion, <hi>Joel</hi> 3.21. The Name of Spiritual <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> is <hi>Jebo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> Shammah, The Lord is there,</hi> Ezek. 48.3<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> And this is a great Affront, to provoke God to his Face, to ſin under his Eye, and in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> ſpecial Preſence, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 65.3. <hi>A People that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> voketh me to anger continually to my face.</hi> Go<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Temple and Habitation was among the and thereby their Guilt was exceeding heightned and aggravated; they did d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> God, and Affront him to his Face: wh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> as the Gentiles might be ſaid, comparati<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, to ſin behind God's Back, becauſe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> ſpecial Preſence was not among them. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Judah was his ſanctuary, and Iſrael his D<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion,</hi> Pſal. 114.2. And how much d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> this increaſe Guilt to be Rebellious, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>work iniquity</hi> in God's Sanctuary, and in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> peculiar Dominion: <hi>Zeph.</hi> 3.5. <hi>The juſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> is in the midſt thereof.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="29" facs="tcp:42338:17"/>
            <p n="3">3dly, It is a heinous Evil to <hi>work iniquity</hi> where the Rule of Righteouſneſs is profeſs'd, preſſed and taught. <hi>I have written to them the great things of my Law, but they counted them ſtrange things,</hi> Hoſ. 8.12. The juſt Lord brings Judgments; that is, his wiſe and holy Laws to light every Morning, and ſets his Laws before Men, <hi>Dan.</hi> 9.10. And they ought to chooſe them, and ſet them before themſelves, <hi>Pſal</hi> 119.30. <hi>I have choſen the way of truth, and thy judgments have I ſet be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore me:</hi> Yet thoſe that <hi>work iniquity</hi> turn to God <hi>their Backs, and not the Face,</hi> Jer. 32.38. And caſt God's Words behind their Backs, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 50.17. Hide their Eyes from it, and are willingly ignorant of it. O what a Shame and Reproach is this to Men, that Beaſts and Birds are better govern'd by Senſe and Inſtinct, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 1.3. <hi>Jer.</hi> 8.7. than Men are by Reaſon, and a written Law of God! How do Men pervert and abuſe their Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon and more than Brutiſie themſelves! When as God taught them more than the Beaſts of the Earth, and made them wiſer than the Fowls of Heaven, <hi>Job.</hi> 15.11.</p>
            <p n="4">4thly, It greatly burthens and provokes God, for Men to <hi>work iniquity</hi> in a Land of Uprightneſs, and where others do work Righteouſneſs: <hi>Iſa.</hi> 26.10. The Wicked <hi>in the land of uprightneſs will deal unjuſtly:</hi> The Land of <hi>Canaan,</hi> where the People of God dwelt, is called the Land of Uprightneſs,
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:42338:18"/>and the People of <hi>Iſrael</hi> are called <hi>Jeſherus, Deut.</hi> 33.26. <hi>There is none like to the God of</hi> Jeſherun. This Name is derived from <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Jaſhar,</hi> which ſignifies to be right; becauſe this was the People that were taught, and profeſs'd Uprightneſs, and Righteouſneſs. Thoſe that are truly the People of God, are ſaid to have wrought his Judgment, <hi>Zeph.</hi> 2.3. Now this augments Guilt, when Perſons ſhall <hi>work iniquity</hi> in a Land of Uprightneſs, where Righteouſneſs is profeſs'd and practi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed by many. Theſe, by their Example, ſhew, that the Yoke of Chriſt is not intole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable, and that Godlineſs is not impoſſible or impracticable: Theſe, by their Strictneſs, Holineſs, and Zeal, do condemn the looſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, profaneneſs, and coldneſs of the <hi>work<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> of <hi>iniquity:</hi> The circumſpect and exact Li<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> they lead, ſhould ſtir up and awaken other that behold them, to a ſerious, exact, and powerful Religion. The very Examples of Saints do teach, and ſhould mightily affect others.</p>
            <p n="5">5thly, It is hainous to <hi>work iniquity,</hi> when Men are taught, That Jeſus Chriſt ga<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e himſelf to <hi>redeem</hi> Men <hi>from all iniquity, Titus</hi> 2.14. and <hi>from a vain converſati<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>y</hi> 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.18. Theſe Men claſh with, and co<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tradict the great End and Deſign of Chriſts Death: They fruſtrate the Sufferings of Chriſt, and reſolve ſtill to be the Servants of Sin, the Portion and Poſſeſſion of Satan, as
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:42338:18"/>if Chriſt's Blood were no valuable Price to purchaſe them, or to oblige them to ceaſe to be their own, and to engage them to be the Lord's Servants and People, as if Chriſt's Blood ſhould purchaſe all for them, but buy nothing of them, nor from them.</p>
            <p n="6">6thly, It is very provoking to <hi>work iniquity</hi> where the Lord uſeth many means to purge Men from Iniquity, <hi>Ezek.</hi> 24.13. <hi>Becauſe I have purged thee, and thou waſt not purged, thou ſhalt not be purged any more from thy ſilthineſs, till I have cauſed my fury to reſt upon thee.</hi> Inſtructions in Righteouſneſs, Reproofs for Sins, Afflictions without, and the Strivings of God's Spirit within, when it counſels Duty, warns of Danger that attends the practice of Iniquity, are all means to purge Men from their Filthineſs. But when God ſhews Men what is Good, and dehorts them from Evil; when he puts them into the Furnace, and kindles the refining Fire, and yet the Droſs of Wickedneſs cleaves cloſe to them, and is not removed from them. This renders the <hi>workers</hi> of <hi>iniquity</hi> more ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noxious to Wrath, and revenging Juſtice. When Men will not ſtop and ceaſe from Sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, then the Fury of God will reſt upon them, and they be expoſed to Torments without end.</p>
            <p n="7">7thly, It mightily provokes God, when Men bear corrupt Fruit, and <hi>work iniquity</hi> in his own Vineyard. God ſets a great Price
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:42338:19"/>and Value on every ſpot and inch of his Vineyard-Ground. Shall that then be clog<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged and peſtered, not only with empty Vines, <hi>Hoſ.</hi> 10.1. but with ſtrange and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>generate Vines, <hi>Jer.</hi> 2.21. ſuch Vines as bear Grapes of Gall, and bitter Cluſters, that yield Wine; that is, the Poiſon of Dra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gons, and the crude Venom of Aſps? Are theſe Grapes fit for the Lord of the Vine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yard to eat of? Is this meet Wine for his to drink? Would it not be intolerably bad for a Child to preſent ſuch Wine to as Earthly Father to poiſon him? And is it not infinitely worſe for Men to render ſuch Wine to their Heavenly Father? Is there any thing he doth more abhor than theſe Cluſters, or more deteſt than this Wine. W<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> God bear always ſuch corrupt and pernici<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap> Trees in his Vineyard.</p>
            <p>The Uſe of this Doctrine is Fourfold:
<list>
                  <item>1. For Terrour.</item>
                  <item>2. For Examination.</item>
                  <item>3. For Exhortation.</item>
                  <item>4. For Caution.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. Uſe is, For Terrour to looſe, ſcand<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous, and profane Chriſtians; they ſhall not ſtill continue in the Kingdom of Chriſt: The time draws near when Chriſt will ſend <hi>forth his Angels,</hi> and <hi>gather</hi> them <hi>out of his Kingdom.</hi> The Harveſt is at hand, when
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:42338:19"/>theſe Tares ſhall be cut out of God's Field The Net will quickly be drawn to the Shoar; and if bad Fiſh be caſt away, God will not value or regard them to all Eternity, but caſt them off, and reject them for ever. Conſider, and weigh all theſe following Particulars, that ſpeak much Terror to the <hi>workers</hi> of <hi>iniquity.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. You ſhall be known: <hi>Prov.</hi> 10.9. <hi>He that perverteth his ways ſhall be known.</hi> Though he veil, diſguiſe, endeavour to conceal him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, yet the day will reveal every Man's State and Work, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.13. Though Hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocrites are as Graves that appear not, <hi>Luk.</hi> 11.44. their Rottenneſs and Wickedneſs appears not to Men, yet God knows their Hearts, <hi>Luke</hi> 16.15. He inſpects their Souls, and diſcovers all the Filth and Wickedneſs that is there. How terrible is Light to Malefa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctors? How bitter and unwelcome is it to Adulterers, and Thieves? They deſire, and affect Darkneſs, that they may be conceal'd, and a Veil caſt over their Wickedneſs: <hi>Job.</hi> 24.17. <hi>The morning is to them as the ſhadow of death: if one know them, they are in the terrours of the ſhadow of death.</hi> Doth God, the Judge, know Men? And will he bring to light all the hidden Things of Darkneſs, and make manifeſt the very Counſels of the Heart, all the ſecret Principles, carnal Motives, corrupt Ends that have byaſs'd and fway'd Sinners in their Actions? And ſhall not this Light of Divine Knowledge, this Day of Divine
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:42338:20"/>Judgment, ſtrike Horrour into the Hearts of ſecure Sinners! Their inſide is ſo bad, that it is a terrible Threatning, that God ſaith, <hi>They ſhall be known.</hi> They have been called by the Worthy, Lovely, Honourable, Glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious Name of <hi>Chriſt;</hi> they have been ſtyled <hi>Chriſtians:</hi> but they have profaned, ſtained, reproached this Excellent Name; therefore they ſhall be diveſted, and ſtripp'd of it; all their Veils, Cloaks, Pretences ſhall be pluck'd off; they ſhall be known what they are, and be called by their own Name. The Wife of <hi>Jeroboam</hi> did diſguiſe her ſelf, and feigned her ſelf to be another Perſon; yet ſhe did not deceive the Lord: He knew her, and informed his blind Prophet <hi>Abijah</hi> of her, 1 <hi>Kings</hi> 14.2, 5, 6. God was acquainted with her Deſign; ſo that when ſhe came to the Prophet's Door, he preſently calls her by her Name, <hi>Come in thou Wife of</hi> Jeroboam, <hi>W<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>y feigneſt thou thy ſelf to be another?</hi> So God will know Sinners in all their Diſguiſes, and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der all their Veils: He will call them by their proper Names; he will ſtyle them no more Chriſtians; but ſay, <hi>You Infidels, you proſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> and ungodly Swearers, Drunkards, Wh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maſters, Lyars, Oppreſſors, and unjuſt Perſons, appear in my preſence, give your Account at my Bar, and Tribunal: You Backſliders in Heart, you rebellious Creatures, hear your Doom and Sentence: You Lying Children, you perfidious Apoſtates, receive your Portion from me.</hi> God
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:42338:20"/>will call you <hi>Droſs,</hi> and <hi>Reprobate Silver.</hi> This ſhall be your Infamy and Reproach, that all the Creatures <hi>are God's Servants,</hi> Pſalm 119.90, 91. But you have been Rebels and Enemies. God's Word hath run very ſwiftly on Earth, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 147.15, 18. All do yield to it and comply with it; but you <hi>workers</hi> of <hi>ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity</hi> have ſtopp'd it, reſiſted it, oppoſed it, and rebelled againſt it. You have been mirey Places and Marſhes, where the Waters of the Sanctuary have been ſtaid and ſtood, <hi>Ezek.</hi> 47.11. Though Men call themſelves of the Holy City, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 48.2. yet God will call them Revolters, Corrupters, Braſs, Iron, Reprobate Silver, Rebellious and Lying Children, <hi>Jer.</hi> 6.28.30.</p>
            <p n="2">2. This will be their great Shame to be known, when it ſhall appear, that all their Religion hath been but embalming a Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſe, painting the Cheeks of a dead Man, and building a beautiful Tomb of Profeſſion over a corrupt and rotten Heart, <hi>Matth.</hi> 23.27. O how ignominious will this be, when it ſhall be manifeſted, that in your beſt Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formances you have but compaſſed God with Lyes, <hi>Hoſ.</hi> 11.12. <hi>Ephraim compaſſeth me a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout with Lyes:</hi> With a lying Profeſſion, lying Services, lying Prayers, lying Praiſes, lying Obedience. Thoſe whoſe Hearts are not ſound in God's Statutes, ſhall be aſhamed, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 119.80. They ſhall be aſhamed of all the Profeſſion they have made; of all the
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:42338:21"/>Works they have performed; of all the Hopes they have entertained; of all the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lations they have pretended: Even in the Great Day they ſhall ariſe to Shame and everlaſting Contempt, <hi>Dan.</hi> 12.2. How will Confuſion cover them, when theſe Graves ſhall be opened? when all Veils ſhall be pulled off, and all the artificial Paint ſhall melt and vaniſh away? when the Filth, Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kedneſs, Deformity of their Souls ſhall ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear? When Satan's Image ſhall be diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerned in them, and his Law ſhall be read in them, in vain have they endeavoured to blind the Eyes of Omniſciency. They could not caſt a Miſt before him, or put a Fallacy and Cheat on him: <hi>Hoſ.</hi> 5.3. <hi>I know Ephraim, and Iſrael is not hid from me</hi> Jer. 13.27. <hi>I have ſeen thy adulteries, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> neighings, and the lewdneſs of thy whoredem.</hi> Sinners only blind their own Eyes, that the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> may not know what they are, and ſee wh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther they are going, but that Satan may lea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> them the more tamely, quietly, and peace<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ably unto Deſtruction.</p>
            <p n="3">3. O what an amazing Diſappoint<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="4 letters">
                  <desc>••••</desc>
               </gap> will the <hi>workers</hi> of <hi>iniquity</hi> meet with, wh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> they ſhall be gathered out of the Kingd<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> of Chriſt! They will look for Light, and God will turn it into groſs Darkneſs, and i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> to the Shadow of Death: <hi>Jer.</hi> 13.16. What dreadful Fruſtration will this be inſtead of a Inheritance, among the Saints in Light, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="37" facs="tcp:42338:21"/>have a Portion with the Wicked in the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gions of Darkneſs, and under the horrours of an eternal Night! How tormenting will this be, to look for Favour and to meet with Fury! to expect Salvation, and then their Eyes ſee their Deſtruction; and inſtead of drinking new Wine of Joy, to drink the Wine of the Wrath of the Almighty, <hi>Job.</hi> 21.20. It was terrible to <hi>Iſrael,</hi> for God, as a Token of his Diſpleaſure, to ſend Thun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der and Rain in Wheat-Harveſt, 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 7.17. And will it not ſtrike more horrour into the <hi>workers</hi> of <hi>iniquity,</hi> when they think to reap a Harveſt of Happineſs, for God to thunder Wrath and Vengeance on them; and to rain Fire and Brimſtone, and an horrible Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peſt on them; and to allot this to them, as the Portion of their Cup? <hi>Pſal.</hi> 11.6. Were not the <hi>Syrians</hi> amazed and terrified, when their Eyes were opened, and they ſaw them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves in the midſt of <hi>Samaria,</hi> in the Hands, and under the Power of their Enemies? 2 <hi>Kings</hi> 16.20. But will it not more aſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh Sinners, to have their Eyes opened at laſt, and to ſee themſelves in the midſt of Devils and damned Souls, under the Power of Satan, and under the Wrath of God? Sinners do drouze and Sleep now, but they will, too late, lift up their Eyes, as <hi>Dives</hi> did, in Hell, <hi>Luke</hi> 16.23. when it will be too late to decline the fatal Blow, to prevent Miſery, and fly from Deſtruction. O how
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:42338:22"/>will this cut Sinners to the Heart! for Jeſus Chriſt to profeſs that which is directly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to their Profeſſion, <hi>Matth.</hi> 7.23. <hi>Then will I profeſs unto them, I never knew you; de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>part from me ye that work iniquity.</hi> They profeſs, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 58.2. to work Righteouſneſs, and to yield Obedience: And this they coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted their Glory. But Chriſt will profeſs to them, <hi>Ye are workers of iniquity:</hi> And this will be to their Ignominy and Reproach Chriſt's Profeſſion concerning Men, is more to be credited than what they profeſs con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning themſelves. Thoſe ſpoken of here, ſeem to be <hi>workers of iniquity</hi> in a more ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual, ſecret, and myſterious way: They acted from old and carnal Principles; they ſerved in the oldneſs of the Letter, not in the newneſs of the Spirit; they did ſome things materially Good, but with regret and rele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctancy, not with pleaſure and delight, <hi>Rom.</hi> 7.6. They were acted by baſe Principles and ſelfiſh Ends; and ſo ſerved themſelves and their Luſts, rather than the Lord Jeſus Chriſt. They failed in the manner of theſe working, and ſo are called <hi>workers of i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity.</hi> The Phariſees thought they well ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved the Laws of God, <hi>Luk.</hi> 15.29. <hi>L<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> theſe many Years do I ſerve thee, neither tr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſed I at any time thy Commandments.</hi> Yet how contrary to this Boaſting is the Charge and Accuſation of the Prophet <hi>Jeremi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>h, Jer.</hi> 32.23. <hi>They have done nothing of all
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:42338:22"/>thou commandedſt them to do. Iſrael</hi> doth cry unto the Lord, <hi>My God, we know thee, Hoſ.</hi> 8.2. Yet here Chriſt profeſſes the contrary, <hi>I never kn<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>w you, Luke</hi> 13.27. Chriſt ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſeth himſelf thus, <hi>Depart from me all ye workers of iniquity.</hi> That Phraſe, <hi>all ye workers of iniquity,</hi> is emphatical: Chriſt will paſs the ſame Doom on <hi>workers of ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity</hi> in the Church, as he doth on thoſe that are out of the Church: He is no Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpecter of Perſons; he hates Iniquity where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever he finds it. Such as turn aſide into crook<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Paths in the Church, ſhall be led forth with the <hi>workers of iniquity:</hi> They ſhall be joined to them, ranked with them, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 125.5. ſhall be accounted of the ſame Body, ſhall receive the ſame Sentence, and feel the ſame, or rather worſer Puniſhments. O how will this vex and perplex, proud Hypocrites! that have thought themſelves, for many Years, to be Members of God's Family; and that they have had much acquaintance and long con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſe with Chriſt, to hear him to reject them as utter Strangers to him, and that he never knew them? O, what a wounding and kil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling Word will this be to them? Surely Stran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers ſhall not dwell with God, or inherit with his Children; they that have ſerved Sin in God's Houſe, <hi>John</hi> 8.34, 35. will be diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covered and caſt out. God that ſaith, <hi>Ye are not my people, and I will not be your God,</hi> Hoſ. 1.9. doth alſo threaten, <hi>Hoſ.</hi> 9.3. <hi>They
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:42338:23"/>ſhall not dwell in the Lord's land.</hi> The Lord's Land is for the Lord's People: If thoſe that were not the Lord's People ſhould not dwell in the Lord's Land, that was but an Earthly <hi>Canaan,</hi> much leſs ſhall they dwell in the Lord's Land, that is a Heavenly Country and <hi>Canaan.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">4thly, They that be gathered out of Chriſt's Kingdom ſhall be deprived of the beſt Good, of True Happineſs; they ſhalt not taſt of Chriſt's Supper, they ſhall not ſit in his Throne; they ſhall not feaſt at his Table, in his Kingdom, or partake of his Glory. To have no part with Chriſt, <hi>John</hi> 13.8. is threatned as the worſt and greateſt Evil; And not to taſt of his Supper, <hi>Luk.</hi> 14.24. On the other hand, To ſee Chriſt's Glory. <hi>John</hi> 17.24. to ſit with him in his Throne, <hi>Revel.</hi> 3.24. to ſit with him at his Table, and to eat and drink with him in his King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, <hi>Luk.</hi> 22.30. is promiſed as the chiefeſt and beſt Good. But ye <hi>workers of iniquity, O what will ye do in the Solemn</hi> and Great Day, <hi>and in the day of the Feaſt of the Lord!</hi> Hoſ. 9.5. Your preſent Pleaſures and De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lights will ceaſe, your Banquet will end and be removed, <hi>Amos</hi> 5.7. you will Famiſh. And when others ſeaſt, you will be ſlain with Thirſt, <hi>Hoſ.</hi> 2.3. When others ſhall drink of the River of God's Pleaſures, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 36.8. yea drink abundantly at the Fountain of Life. You will roar and howl, when others ſhall
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:42338:23"/>ſing and rejoyce. <hi>Job</hi> complains, <hi>Job</hi> 9.25. That his Days did ſlee away, they ſaw no Good: But <hi>workers of iniquity</hi> will more dreadfully and dolefully complain, That Millions of Years do paſs over them, yet in them all they ſee no Good.</p>
            <p n="5">5thly, Thoſe that are gathered out of Chriſt's Kingdom, are without hope of ever returning to it, or being let in, and received into it for ever, <hi>Luk.</hi> 13.25. When once the Maſter of the Houſe is riſen up, and hath ſhut the Door, he will never riſe up again to open it; then it will be too late to knock, or plead for Admiſſion; the Bride<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>groom hath done Wooing; the great Shep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>herd will call no more; the gracious Phyſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cian will practiſe no more; the Ladder which joins Heaven and Earth together will be drawn up, and all Treaties of Peace will be at an end: As when God did ſhut the Door of the Ark, <hi>Gen.</hi> 7.16. <hi>Noah</hi> was included, and his Family, and all the reſt of the World were excluded, though they did cry never ſo bitterly, groan never ſo deeply, plead never ſo earneſtly, yet, they could not be admitted, they could not be received; the time of God's Patience was at an end, and the Day of his Wrath and Vengeance was come. So Chriſt will not be entreated, will not relent; as Sinners hardned their Hearts in time, ſo Chriſt will harden his Heart to Eternity; as they had no love for Chriſt, ſo
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:42338:24"/>he hath no Bowels to yearn towards them, no Boſom to receive them: Their Condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion was once hopeful, but now it is deſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 5.2. The Hands of Chriſt were once ſtretched out, <hi>Prov.</hi> 1.24. to allure and receive them; but now the Arms of Chriſt will be ſtretched out to puniſh them: They did their own and Satan's Will in time, and they muſt now ſuffer God's Will to Eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity: They were once invited, and impor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tun'd earneſtly to come into his Kingdom; but then they ſhall be violently thruſt out of it, and everlaſtingly debarr'd from it. There is a vaſt difference between theſe two Expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions, <hi>Luke</hi> 14.23. <hi>Compel them to come us</hi> and that in <hi>Luke</hi> 13.28. <hi>And you your ſelves thruſt out.</hi> They that have wearied the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tience, and ſlighted the Grace of God, ſhall be eternally cut off from ſeeing of him, and converſing with him. Mercy will iſſue in Severity, and Patience will end undetermi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate in Fury.</p>
            <p n="6">6. Thoſe that are gathered out of Chriſt's Kingdom, ſhall behold the Happineſs, Feaſt, and Glory of the Saints of God, and gnaſh their Teeth for envy and rage, ſeeing what others enjoy, and they themſelves are depri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved of, <hi>Luke</hi> 13.28. <hi>There ſhall be weeping, and gnaſhing of teeth, when ye ſhall ſee Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham, Iſaac, and Jacob, and all the Prophets in the Kingdom of God, and you your ſelves thruſt out.</hi> This ſhall heighten the Saints Felicity,
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:42338:24"/>to ſee the Miſery and Torments of the Dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned. <hi>Iſaiah</hi> 66.24. <hi>They ſhall go forth, and look upon the carcaſes of the men that have tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſed againſt me: for their worm ſhall not die, neither ſhall their Fire be quenched:</hi> thus <hi>Eſau,</hi> and other Reprobates ſhall eternally ſerve <hi>Ja<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>b,</hi> and the other Elect, the miſery of the Damned, ſhall cauſe them more to admire the Mercy extended to them: their weep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings and howlings ſhall heighten Saints Songs, Praiſes and Thankſgivings, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 58.10. <hi>The righteous ſhall rejoyce when he ſeeth the vengeance:</hi> ſo on the other hand, this ſhall encreaſe and heighten the Miſery of the <hi>Workers of Ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity,</hi> that they ſhall ſee the Feaſt, the Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, the Glory of the Saints, that they are deprived of, 2 <hi>Kings,</hi> 7.1, 2. <hi>Eliſha</hi> prophe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſieth of a ſudden plenty the very next day in <hi>Samaria,</hi> where they had been under a long and grievous Famine: A Lord in <hi>Samaria</hi> would not believe it, the Prophet tells him, <hi>that yet he ſhould ſee it, but ſhould not eat thereof:</hi> So Sinners now will not believe what Reſt, what Honour, what a Feaſt Saints ſhall enjoy, when <hi>they ſit down with Abraham, Iaac, and Jacob, in the Kingdom of God,</hi> Matth. 8.11. but yet they ſhall one day ſee it, but ſhall not ſhare in it, nor partake of it. O how will their Hearts fret and rage, to ſee thoſe that they have ſo much deſpiſed, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, and abhorred, to ſit in the Throne, when they ſhall be made Footſtools; to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joy
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:42338:25"/>the greateſt Plenty, when they ſhall lye under eternal Penury, and want of all Good.</p>
            <p n="7">7. This may affright and terriſie the <hi>Work<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers of Iniquity,</hi> that they, as vile and worth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs Creatures ſhall be caſt away, Matth. 13.48. the bad Fiſh ſhall be caſt away as thoſe that God hath no eſteem of, Love to, o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Delight in; they have caſt away the Law of the Lord, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 5.24. and now they them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves ſhall be caſt away; they would not put away the Luſts of their Hearts, the Evil of their Doings, and now therefore they muſt be put away as Droſs, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 119.119. <hi>Thou puttest away all the wicked of the Ea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> as Droſs:</hi> But this is not all; the Tares ſhall be caſt into a Furnace of unquenchable Fire, Matth. 13.12. It is honourable to be Trees for Fruit, but it is diſgracefull and reproach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful to be Trees for Fuel; Hay ſerves for Food to Cattel, but Tares do ſerve only to heat the Oven, and to burn in the Furnace. O how dreadful is this for to be caſt into a Furnace heated by the Anger and Fury of God? Can we imagine how terrible that Fire is, which is kindled by incenſed Juſtice, and blown up by the Breath of an angry God? a Fire that will indeed devour all that is pleaſant, and coniume all that is ſweet and gratefull in Life, yet leave ſtill a Being to feel Miſery, and endure Eternal Torments. We ſhould be amazed to ſee a Wiſp of Straw,
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:42338:25"/>a Bundle of Tares to hold out one day, and not be conſumed; but this is a great Miracle of the Power of God, to uphold and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve Sinners to be an eternal Mark for God to ſhoot at, an eternal Footſtool for him to tread on: Eternal Veſſels for him to drop his Wrath, and pour out his Fury into: The Evil of Sin, doth not conſume, is not expi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ated by all the Torments of the <hi>workers of iniquity;</hi> and ſo their Miſery cannot abate, their Puniſhments cannot leſſen, nor the Fire go out: they ſuffer from God and hate him; they endure Blows and Wounds from him, and blaſpheme him for them: they Rebelled againſt God, they ſuffered Sin and Satan to Rule in them, and now full ſore a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt their Wills, God will Reign over them with an out-ſtretched Arm, and Fury pou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red out, <hi>Ezek.</hi> 20.33. they would not come under Chriſt's Paſtoral Rod, <hi>Ezek</hi> 20.37. but they muſt be forced to fall under Chriſt's Iron Rod, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 2.9. their Sin did grieve God, and God's Sentence, and the Execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of it will eternally ſting, and vex them. Oh, it is dreadful for Sinners to be preſerved in being, for their hurt; to have an immor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal Exiſtence, that they may feel an immor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal Puniſhment, Miſery and Torment! If Chriſt that was a green Tree, <hi>Luke</hi> 23.31. that was full of the vital Sap of Holineſs and Righteouſneſs, and did continually abound in ſpiritual Fruit, had yet ſuch a Fire of
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:42338:26"/>Wrath burning againſt him, and kindled on him, when as Evil Fruits were only hanged on him by imputation, but did never grow in, or on him, what muſt dry Trees expect that are deſtitute of the Life of God, and did ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver bear Fruit to Chriſt, what an everlaſting Furnace, what an Eternal Fire will be their Portion? Chriſt could paſs the Cup from him by his drinking of it, <hi>Mat.</hi> 26.42. but <hi>workers of iniquity</hi> ſhall drink of the Cup of God's Fury, yet it ſhall never paſs from them, but ſtay at their Lips, and be ſuck'd and ſoak into their Souls.</p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>Uſe.</hi> I would now put you on the Search, Trial, and Examination of your ſelves: Are you truly Members of, and ſincere Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects in this Kingdom of God? Are you ſuch as ſhall ſtay in the Kingdom of God, or ſuch as ſhall be gathered out of it? There is a great deal of difference between treading in God's Courts, <hi>Iſaiah</hi> 1.12. and growing in God's Houſe, or being planted and flou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhing in God's Courts, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 92.13. thoſe that only tread in God's Courts, may not ſtay in his Houſe, <hi>John</hi> 8.35. but may be dri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven out of it. <hi>Hoſ.</hi> 9.15. <hi>I will drive them out of my houſe; I will love them no more:</hi> but thoſe that are planted by God, and are green Olive-Trees in the Houſe of God, they ſhall never wither, or be rooted up, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 52.8. <hi>they truſt in the mercy of God for
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:42338:26"/>ever and ever,</hi> and mercy will follow them all their days, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 23.6. and mercy will be built up for ever, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 89.2. It is worth the while to enquire what we are, and whoſe we are, that we may not flatter and deceive our own Souls. In a Family there are Sons and Servants <hi>John</hi> 4.35. in a Great Houſe there are Veſſels of Gold and Silver, and Veſſels of Wood and Earth: in great Cities, as in <hi>Rome</hi> of old, they did diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſh the Inhabitants into two ſorts, the <hi>Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venae,</hi> or Strangers; the <hi>Cives,</hi> or Citizens that were born and bred there. O conſider, Are you Titular or Real? Are you Tranſient or Abiding Subjects in Chriſt's Kingdom? Are ye reſcued and delivered from the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſe Prince, and contrary Kingdom? Men are born under the Law of Sin, <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.2. and under the power of Satan, <hi>Acts</hi> 26.18. the God of this World is their Father, <hi>John</hi> 8.44. the Prince of this World is their King. Oh therefore ask this ſerious Queſtion, Is the Prince of the World caſt out of your Hearts? <hi>John</hi> 12.31. <hi>now ſhall the Prince of the World be caſt out:</hi> And are you pluckt out of his Paw, reſcued out of his. King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom,? <hi>Col.</hi> 1.13. <hi>Who hath delivered us from the power of darkneſs,</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>: the Father hath by a ſtrong hand, by a mighty arm pluckt, and ſnatched his Redeemed from the Power of Darkneſs: Ignorance and Sin are Darkneſſes, and Satan is the Power and
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:42338:27"/>Prince of Darkneſs; he rules Men by their Ignorance and Luſts; and therefore he is ſtiled <hi>the ruler of the darkneſs of this world,</hi> Epheſ. 6.12. Ignorance and Sin have a ſtrange Power over Souls, as if they were rightful and lawful Powers, and Satan's Kingdom is grounded and built on them: Sinners know not what they do, whither they go, whom they ſerve; and hence it is they do ſo readily and willingly yield them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves to obey the Commands of theſe Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, that hoodwink them, and hurry them on to Deſtruction: Are your Eyes opened? Are Satan's Snares and Sin's Bonds broken? Are you turned <hi>from darkneſs to light; from the power of Satan to God,</hi> Acts 26.18. are you <hi>made free from the law of ſin and death?</hi> Rom. 8.2. darkneſs did chain the Egyptians in their Places, that they did not remove, or go about, <hi>Exod.</hi> 10.22, 23. but when the Light returned, then they were ſet at Liberty to walk about, and work: ſo have you known the Truth of Chriſt, and been made free by it, <hi>John</hi> 8.32. Is the Veil of Ignorance drawn off from your Minds? And are the Chains of Luſt fallen off from your Wills? A Veil is a Reſtraint and Bondage on the Eye. Thoſe that do not ſee the Evil of Sin, will not fly from it; they that behold not the Excellency of the Kingdom of God will not preſs into it.</p>
            <pb n="49" facs="tcp:42338:27"/>
            <p n="2">2ly, Are you tranſlated into the Kingdom of Chriſt? <hi>Col.</hi> 1.14. We are born in Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tan's Kingdom as our Country and Natural Soil; but by Grace we are led forth as a Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lony into the Kingdom of Chriſt, which is, to a natural Man, a ſtrange Land, and a new Soil. But how are Men tranſlated into the Kingdom of Chriſt? ſurely it is by effe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctual Calling, and Regeneration. We are called as rational Creatures, and we are re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>generated, as corrupt and impotent Creatures. God is ſaid to call us to his Kindom and Glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, 1 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 2.12. Except a Man be born a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain, he cannot ſee, he cannot enter into the Kingdom of God, <hi>John</hi> 3.3.5. He can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not ſee, or underſtand that there is ſuch a King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, or be willing to enter into it, or be fitted to enjoy the Benefits and Bleſſings of it: As Children muſt be born to be the Subjects of Earthly Kings; ſo Men muſt be re-born to be the Subjects of the Heavenly King. This is for the Honour and Glory of Chriſt's King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, that none can paſs into it, but by Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>generation: Thoſe that are the genuine, and true Citizens of <hi>Zion,</hi> and Members of the Church, are ſaid to be born there, <hi>Pſ.</hi> 87.4, 6. Thoſe that God writes up as Citizens of <hi>Zion,</hi> are ſuch as are born there. God's Regiſter, and the Church's Roll, or Cata<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logue, do many times much differ. The Church owns thoſe for her Children, that God doth not acknowledge for his Sons and Daughters: The Church takes in thoſe that
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:42338:28"/>God will turn out: God will repute none his Jewels, call none his own, but they that are born again of his Word and Spirit, <hi>Mal.</hi> 3.17. 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.23. <hi>John</hi> 3.6. And indeed, How can Men poſſibly be Subjects in God's Kingdom, except they have ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual Minds, converted Wills, heavenly Affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions? A vain Mind, a carnal Heart will only flatter and lye to Chriſt, <hi>Matth.</hi> 3.2. <hi>Repent, for the Kingdom of Heaven is at hand:</hi> Men cannot be Subjects in, or Heirs of the Kingdom of God, without Faith and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance. The good Seed are the Children of the Kingdom, <hi>Matth.</hi> 13.35. Thoſe that receive the Word, are begotten by the Word of Truth, <hi>John</hi> 1.18. that have it rooted in their Souls, ſpreading and prevailing in their Hearts, theſe are good Seed: Jeſus Chriſt doth not only ſow Doctrinal Truths, but living Chriſtians: He begets Sons and Daughters to God; by the Word they are changed by, and born of the Word, and ſo are called Seed. That Word is ſtyled the Good Word, <hi>Heb.</hi> 6.5. and they that are born of it, are therefore called Good Seed. Divine <hi>Chryſoſtom,</hi> a <hi>Grecian</hi> Orator, in one of his Orations, derides the Folly of the <hi>Grecians,</hi> that did call that one Man's Statue, which was carved to reſemble, and ſet up to the Honour of another. There was no new carving of, or alteration in the Statue, but only the Title of it was changed. And
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:42338:28"/>do Men ſo eaſily paſs out of the Kingdom of Satan, into the Kingdom of Chriſt, on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly by the changing of a Name? No, there muſt be another kind of Alteration: There muſt not only be a new Name, but a new Heart, a new Nature, <hi>Ezek.</hi> 36.26. 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.4. O deſcend into your Hearts! What Experience have you of the Work of the Spirit, in dethroning Satan, and inthroning Chriſt in your Hearts; deſtroying the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of Sin, and exalting the Kingdom of God. Conſult your own Souls about this: Can you be totally ignorant of it, if ſuch a change hath been made in you? Doth not every one take notice of publick Revolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions in Government, if one Prince dye, or be depoſed, and another ſucceed, and be ſet up in his Place? And hath there been ſo great a ſpiritual Revolution in thy Soul, hath Satan been caſt out, and hath Chriſt entred to dwell and rule in thy Heart, and haſt thou no knowledge of it? Haſt thou no experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence of a new light ſet up in thy Mind? a new Byaſs put upon thy Will? new Motions raiſed in thy Affections towards ſpiritual and ſupernatural Objects?</p>
            <p n="3">3dly, Are the Laws of this Holy King, and of this Heavenly Kingdom writ in thy Heart? according to that promiſe of the new Covenant, <hi>Jer.</hi> 31.33. <hi>I will write my laws in their hearts, and put them into their inner parts.</hi> This is the Glory of Chriſt, that he
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:42338:29"/>writes his Laws in the Table of the Mind and Will, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.3. His Subjects not only know, but love and ask his Laws. Their Obedience to them is not forced or feigned; but they obey from the Heart. <hi>Rom.</hi> 6.17. They delight in the Law of God according to the inward Man, <hi>Rom.</hi> 7.22. God's Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects are thus deſcribed, That the Law of God is in their Hearts. It is not an urging Letter without, but a vital Principle with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in: <hi>Pſal.</hi> 37.31. <hi>The law of his God is in his heart:</hi> and <hi>Iſa.</hi> 51.7. <hi>Hearken unto me, ye that know righteouſneſs, the People in whoſe heart is my law.</hi> Chriſt plants ſuch Diſpoſitions, ſuch Inclina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions as are ſuitable and agreeable to the Law of God, and may be ſtyled a counter p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>t of it, and do anſwer to it: <hi>Pſal.</hi> 119.112. <hi>I have enclined my heart to perform thy Statutes always, even to the end.</hi> This is a writing that doth exact and ennoble the Table, th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> is, the Subject of it: And this is an high Act of Grace, when God doth not only write his Laws to us, but in us. Do you ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prove, allow, delight in the Laws of God<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Do your Souls break for the Longings yee have to, and after them? that they might be more revealed to you, and impreſſed on you. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 119.20.</p>
            <p n="4">4thly, Are you led by the Spirit of the King? <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.9, 14. <hi>If any man hath not the Spirit of Chriſt, he is none of his. As many as are led by the Spirit of God, are the Se<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="53" facs="tcp:42338:29"/>of God.</hi> This is a wonderful and a great Myſtery, that the Spirit of the King is in his Subjects, and they all make but one my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtical Body; and the Spirit is as the Soul that animates this Body. Were ever King and Subjects ſo nearly linked, united, related to each other? Chriſt is not only a politick Head that gives Laws, but as a natural Head that giveth Life. The Spirit that influenced Chriſt, acts them; the Spirit that reſides in Chriſt, dwells alſo in them. The People of Chriſt muſt needs therefore be a free and willing People. Do not the Members of the natural Body, without Regret or Relu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctancy, obey the Dictates of the Head? How powerful, yet how eaſie and ſweet is the Government of the Head over the Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers? Chriſt's Spirit doth not only teach and direct, but powerfully bend and encline the Will to walk, yea to run in the way of God's Commandments, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 119.32. Saints do not deſire the way to Heaven to be made broader, but their Hearts to be made larger; to have their light and love encreaſed. The Spirit is ſtyled, A Spirit of Revelation, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 1.17. A Spirit of Life, <hi>Rom</hi> 8.2. A Free Spirit, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 51.12. A Spirit that makes us free and forward in our Obedience. We are not only reſtrained from Sin by an outward Prohibition, but we hate it; our Nature is averſe from it, and abhors it. We are not meerly conſtrain'd by an imperious and ur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:42338:30"/>Command, enforced with terrible Threat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nings, but ſweetly and powerfully enclined by an inward Diſpoſition and vital Principle. Do you love your Heavenly Maſter, and would not go free from him, but be more ſubjected to him? when others do break the Yoke of God, and do burſt his Bonds, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 2.3. <hi>Jer.</hi> 5.5. Do you put your Necks in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Chriſt's Yoke? <hi>Matth.</hi> 11.29. and bend your ſelves with his Laws, as pleaſant, light, and ornamental Chains? <hi>Iſa.</hi> 45.14. <hi>They ſhall come after thee in Chains.</hi> Kings and No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles are willingly bound with theſe Chains, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 149.8. As the deſire of <hi>Iſrael</hi> was to <hi>Saul,</hi> and to have him to rule over the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 9.20. ſo the Nations did run to Chriſt, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 55.5. and deſire him to rule o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver them, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 11.10. The Gentiles are ſaid to ſeek to him: And alſo the converted Jews <hi>Hoſ.</hi> 3.5. ſhould ſeek to him, as a King, that he might give Law to them, and rule over them. Chriſt's Kingdom is not forced and obtruded on his People, but voluntarily choſen, and freely ſubmitted to.</p>
            <p n="5">5thly, Examin how are your Hearts and Lives ordered: 1. How are your Minds, Wills, Affections ordered, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 9.7. Jeſus ſits on a ſpiritual Throne to order it: The Soul is Chriſt's Throne, and till he ſits and rules in it, all is diſorderly. The Thoughts are <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ain, the Will rebellious, the Aſſections vile and inordinate, as at firſt the Water over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>whelmed
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:42338:30"/>and covered all, <hi>Gen.</hi> 1.2. till <hi>God ſaid, Let the waters be gathered into one place,</hi> Gen. 1.9. and then <hi>dry land appeared;</hi> and a Place was prepared for Mens Habitation<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> So while there is nothing but a ſpiritual Chaos, Self-love, as a Sea, covers all, ſwallows up all true Love to God, and Man: But when God, by his Grace, doth gather the Affections into their proper Chanels, and unto their right Objects: When God bounds, banks, and limits them, then dry Land, in a ſpiritual ſence, appears for God's Habitation in the Soul; then room and place is made for him. Are your Hearts directed into the Love of God? 2 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 8.5. And are you taught of God to love your Brethren? 1 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 4.9. Then Self love is ordered, and is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fined within its due and proper Bounds.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Are your Converſations ordered aright? Do you ſet God's Laws before you, <hi>Pſalm</hi> 119.30. as the Rule of your Hearts, Words, Actions? Is it your true and greateſt deſign to pleaſe God, 1 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 4.1. and to be accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted with him? 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.9. When Chriſt comes into the Soul, he Judges, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 2.4. he Reproves, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 11.3. Jeſus Chriſt cenſures what is contrary and diſpleaſing to God: He rebukes Mens Luſts; he puts a new Byaſs on the Will, and enclines the Soul to a new way and walk, <hi>Jer.</hi> 3.17. <hi>They ſhall call Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruſalem</hi> (that is, the Church; that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>, Spiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual <hi>Jeruſalem</hi>) <hi>the Throne of the Lord, and all
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:42338:31"/>the nations ſhall be gathered unto it, to the name of the Lord, to Jeruſalem: they ſhall walk no more after the Imaginations of their evil hearts.</hi> But they that walk in the <hi>light of the Lord,</hi> Iſa. 2.5. and <hi>in the fear of the Lord, and in the comfort of his holy Spirit,</hi> Acts 9.31. If thou doſt ſtill walk in thy own Counſels, and in the Luſts of thine own Heart, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 51.12. and in the common way of the World, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 8.11. and, as other Gentiles do, in the Vanity of thy Mind, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 4.17. beſure thou haſt had no Experience of the Kingdom of Chriſt come into, and ſet up in thy Heart: If thy Heart be caſt into a new Mould, <hi>Rom.</hi> 6.7. and brought under a new Lord and Law, thy Soul muſt needs ſtee<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> new courſe. As Heaven and Hell do vaſtly differ, ſo do the narrow and broad way ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedingly differ, that lead to a bleſſed, and miſerable Eternity: You reproach and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grace the Kingdom of Chriſt, if your Hearts are not leavened with Faith and Love, and if your Converſations are not ordered better than others. Chriſt's Sheep come and go at the Direction and Command of the great Shepherd; but others, out of Chriſts Kingdom, are as wild Beaſts that run to and fro, move here and there at their own Plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure; they are turned up and down by the dictates of a vain Mind, and wicked Will: but yet if you are Chriſt's true Subjects, you will not be brought under the power of
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:42338:31"/>tempting Objects without, or reigning Luſts within, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6.12.</p>
            <p n="3">3. <hi>Uſe,</hi> Shall the <hi>workers of iniquity</hi> be ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thered out of Chriſt's Kingdom, then I would Exhort you ſincerely to ſubject your ſelves to the Lord Jeſus Chriſt, as your King. Let not your Lips ſlatter, and your Tongue lye to Jeſus Chriſt; but indeed take Chriſt's Yoke, come under his paſtoral Rod, enter into his Fold, and into the Bond of the Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant, <hi>Matth.</hi> 11.29. <hi>Ezek.</hi> 20.37. <hi>John</hi> 10.9.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Conſider, Jeſus Chriſt is not ſond of, or ſets a value on, neither is he pleaſed and delighted with empty Names and Titles: <hi>Matth.</hi> 7.21. <hi>It is not every one that ſaith Lord, Lord, that ſhall enter into the Kingdom of Heaven.</hi> Chriſt will not own, approve, admit ſuch in the Great Day; a form of Godlineſs will yield but a vain Image of Happineſs. Would an earthly King be ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfied, if Rebels did call him their Lord, and would receive his Picture into their Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, but did ſhut out his Perſon? And will the King of Glory be appeaſed and quieted with a Picture of Piety, or with a cold and dead form of Religion? We are bid not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to give the Hand to the Lord, 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 30.8. (ſo it is in the Original, and ſo in the Margin, with alluſion to thoſe that did make Bargains, and to conclude them, did ſtrike
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:42338:32"/>or give their Hands to each other) but we are alſo required to give our Hearts to the Lord, <hi>Prov.</hi> 23.26. The Life of the natural Man is but a vain ſhew of Life, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 39.6. <hi>Surely every man walketh in a vain ſhew:</hi> And will it advantage us to add a vain ſhew of Religion to a vain Shew of Life? Can Men make up a Summ to enrich them, by multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plying Cyphers? And Hypocrite is ſtyled a vain Man, <hi>James</hi> 2.20. <hi>But wilt thou know, O vain man, that faith without works is dead.</hi> And the formal Prayers of Hypocrites are called <hi>Vanity,</hi> Job. 35.12, 13. <hi>Men cry, but none giveth anſwer.</hi> But why are Prayers this fruitleſs and ineffectual? the next Words toll us the Cauſe: <hi>Surely God will not hear vanity, neither will the Almighty regard it.</hi> Both na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural and inſtituted Worſhip is to be a Wine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs, <hi>Matth.</hi> 21.33. and ſo to ſqueeze and draw out the Juice and Quinteſſence of Grace that is in the Soul, elſe Chriſt will not regard Lip-labour, and bodily Service. The Heart is Chriſt's Houſe and Throne; the Mind and Will are the Tables he writes his Laws in, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.3. He requires the beſt Room, the Gueſt Chamber: It is an Affront, and an Indignity to Chriſt, to be thruſt into the Stable again, or to be en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertained only in an out Room. Will a Maſter reward a Servant, that only wears his Livery, but doth not his Work.</p>
            <pb n="59" facs="tcp:42338:32"/>
            <p n="2">2dly, Jeſus will look into the Souls, and ſee through all outſide Shews and Appear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ances, <hi>Iſaiah</hi> 11.3. Jeſus judgeth not accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the ſight of his eyes, nor reproveth according to the hearing of his ears. Jeſus Chriſt doth not ſtop, or ſtay on the ſurface and outſide of things, neither doth he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive Intelligence and Information from o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers that may be miſtaken themſelves, and ſo might deceive and abuſe him, but he hath a Window into the Breaſts and Boſoms of Sinners, he ſearcheth the Hearts, he trieth the Reins, he weigheth the Spirits of Men, he detects inward Poverty, Emptineſs and Filth, <hi>Matt.</hi> 12.44. he finds it out, if the Houſe be empty of Grace, and deſtitute of the Spirit, at beſt but ſwept from groſſer Sins and Crimes, and garniſhed with Morality, and a Form of Godlineſs; but rather it was ſwept and garniſhed, and fitted for the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn of the unclean Spirit into it, <hi>Matt.</hi> 12.45. Chriſt diſcerned the Houſe of the Soul to be ſwept from all ſpiritual Good, and gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed in Satan's Eye with ungodlineſs and unrighteouſneſs. Chriſt will diſcover thoſe that make a fair Show of Religion; that have a Name to live, that yet they are really dead, <hi>Rev.</hi> 3.1. he looks through the beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiful Sepulchre and Tomb, and ſeeth the Filth and Rettenneſs of a carnal and dead Heart underneath. The Jews did account
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:42338:33"/>that Men were defiled by touching or walk<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing over a Grave; and therefore when a Grave was ſunk, and did not appear, <hi>Luke</hi> 11.44. they uſed to go forth in the Day be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore their Feſtivals, and caſt Lime, or Chalk on them, and ſo by whiting the ground, to give notice of a Grave, that Perſons might not come near it, and be polluted by it. A Learned Man doth think that Jeſus Chriſt alludes to this Cuſtom, when he calls the Hypocritical Scribes and Phariſees <hi>graves that did not appear;</hi> but he by his Reprooſs and Diſcoveries of them, did white them, that ſo Perſons might know them, beware, and take heed of them. There is not the cloſeſt Hypocrite in the World, but Chriſt can find him out, and white him, <hi>Iſaiah</hi> 11.3. Chriſt is of <hi>quick understanding,</hi> or of quick ſcent and ſmell, (as it is in the Hebrew) in, and about <hi>the Fear of the Lord,</hi> he doth wind he doth ſcent Hypocriſie, though it be veil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and cloaked over with a beautiful Shew of Religion and Righteouſneſs. If you are Hypocrites, and think to blind Chriſt's Eyes with a ſpecious Form of Godlineſs without the Power of it, you are guilty of a kinded Blaſphemy. If you think that Chriſt may be couzened with your Caſed Pieces, and doth not know your counterfeit and braſs Money, <hi>Rev.</hi> 2.9. <hi>I know the blaſphemy of them that ſay they are Jews and are not, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="61" facs="tcp:42338:33"/>are the Synagogue of Satan.</hi> It is no leſs than Blaſphemy for thee ſo to think to put a Falla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy and Cheat on Chriſt, who knoweth all the hidden things, and will bring to light all the deep Counſels of it, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4.5. he will lay open all the ſecret Luſts, all the corrupt and baſe Ends that inſluenced and ſwayed Men under a Profeſſion of Religion and the practice of ſome outward Duties.</p>
            <p n="3">3dly, Men may call Chriſt Lord, and yet repeat, and act over all the Indignities that were offered to Chriſt by the unbelieving Jews, that were his Enemies; they Crow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned Chriſt, but it was with Thorns; they put a Scepter into his hand, but it was a Reed; they ſaluted him, and ſaid, <hi>Hail, King of the Jews;</hi> but all this was but in mockery and deriſion, for they ſmote Chriſt on the head, <hi>Matt.</hi> 27.29, 30. and are not many nominal and outſide Chriſtians guilty of the ſame things in a Myſtery, their hearing ſome Sermons now and then, with a wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dring and roving Mind, with a drouſie Ear; their repeating ſome Forms of Prayer in a cold and heartleſs manner, without Under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding, or Faith, without inward Groans, ſpiritual Wreſtlings and Importunities; their owning ſome Doctrinal Points of Religion, and practiſing ſome juſt things as to the Mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of them, is the Reed they put into Chriſt's Hand; ſome outward Acknowledg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments they make of his Lordſhip and Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minion
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:42338:34"/>over them, but in the mean time they Crown Chriſt with Thorns, by their Oaths, Curſes and Lies; they ſmite Chriſt by their Drunkenneſs, their Uncleanneſs, their ſcorning at Godlineſs, their Reproach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing them that will not profane the Lord's. Day as they do, and will not neglect God's Worſhip in their Families as they do, and will not run with them to the ſame Exceſs of Riot, drink in Iniquity, and roll in Filth and Uncleanneſs as they do; they take no care to engage their Hearts to Chriſt, to keep them with all diligence, to watch over their Tongues, to order their Converſations aright, and ſpend their Time well. As the Jews were incenſed againſt Chriſt, <hi>Iſaiaha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</hi> 24. they pretended he did forbid to pay Tribute to <hi>Caeſar,</hi> and would juſtle him out of his Throne: when as the true Cauſe of their Controverſie with, and Enmity againſt Chriſt was, that he would thruſt Satan out of his Throne, and did forbid Sinners to pay Tribute to their Luſts: So Men now are en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raged againſt Chriſt for the ſame Reaſon, becauſe his Holy Will croſſes their cornat wills, his Commands claſh with their Luſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, and he reſtrains them from the Pleaſures of Sin that are ſo ſweet to them, and calls theat to Purity and Strictneſs in Religion, which is ſo bitter and unpleaſing to them. Will Chriſt accept of Honour in Words, when it is joyned with Reproach in Deeds? Wiſt
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:42338:34"/>verbal Friendſhip be regarded, when accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panied with real Enmity? Will Chriſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pute thoſe his Subjects, that ſerve his Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, and gratifie Satan and their own Luſts? Shall pretended Obedience bring Men unto Heaven, and real Diſobedience not throw them to Hell? Shall a Lye ingratiate Men with God, and true Impiety not render them odious to God?</p>
            <p n="4">4thly, Conſider Jeſus Chriſt will ſet up his Kingdom in the World, and at laſt Rule over you, whether you will or no: As none can hinder the riſing of the Sun, or obſtruct the blowing of the Wind; ſo all the oppoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and rage of the World ſhall not hinder the riſing of the <hi>Son of Righteouſneſs</hi> Mal. 4.2. and of the <hi>Glory of the Lord,</hi> Iſa. 60.1. nor obſtruct the blowing of the Wind of the Spirit, <hi>Acts</hi> 2.2. This mighty ruſhing Wind filled the World with the Doctrine of Chriſt, as that Wind at <hi>Pentecoſt</hi> filled the Houſe where the Apoſtles of Chriſt were ſitting. Though Kings, and the great Men of the World, did join their Counſels, and unite their Strength and Force to keep down Chriſt's Kingdom, and to ſuppreſs the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginnings of it, yet he that ſate in the Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vens did laugh at all their Policy and Power, and had all their Attempts and Endeavours in deriſion, and did prevail, notwithſtanding all their Malice, to ſet his King on his Holy Hill of <hi>Zion,</hi> Pſal. 2.4, 5, 6. And Chriſt did
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:42338:35"/>reign over his Enemies full fore againſt their Wills. They deſigned and endeavoured to break Chriſt's Bands in ſunder; but Chriſt did break them with his Rod of Iron, and daſh them to pieces as a Potter's Veſſel, <hi>Pſalm</hi> 2.9. The Jews perſecuted Chriſt's Apoſtles and Servants, and ſent many of them to Heaven on this Meſſage and Errand, to tell Chriſt how the Jews are bent againſt his Kingdom, and would not have Chriſt to reign over them, <hi>Luke</hi> 19.14. yet Jeſus Chriſt did gather, ſubdue, and convert ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of their Nation to be his Subjects; and as for the Body of the People that continued in their Unbelief and Diſobedience, this Glorious King ſent forth his Armies, that is, the Romans, and deſtroyed them, and bunt up their City, <hi>Mat.</hi> 22.7. And at the laſt Day, he will ſeverely ſentence and puniſh the Rebellious: <hi>Luke</hi> 19.27. <hi>As for theſe mine enemies that would not have me to rule over them, bring them before me, and let them be ſlain in my preſence.</hi> Though they do not al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low Chriſt a Throne in their Souls, yet Chriſt will erect his Tribunal, and ſit <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> Judgment on all that oppoſe and ſtand o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> againſt him. Where Grace doth not reign, Juſtice will reign: If Chriſt doth not coe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demn and execute Sin in us, he will condem<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> and execute us: Either Satan's Works and Luſts muſt be cruſhed and deſtroyed in us, or we muſt be cut off, and periſh for ever.
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:42338:35"/>Thoſe that Chriſt doth not prune, he will fell; thoſe that he is not a refining Fire to, he will be a conſuming Fire; if the Old Man be not pierced and wounded by Chriſt's Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rows, the Souls of Men muſt be Chriſt's Mark, and feel the edge and point of his glittering Sword. If Chriſt doth not rule to ſave Men, he will rule to deſtroy them. The Civil Law mentions ſome Malefactors that are called
<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Vid. Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciamin: 1 Lib. inſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tut. Tit.</hi> 12. <hi>Sect.</hi> 6.</note> 
               <hi>Servi Poenae,</hi> ſuch as were condemn'd to row at the Oar, or to dig in the Mines; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they did not obey the Law, and live honeſtly, they were ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jected to hard Service, and did live miſerably: So thoſe that are not Subjects to Chriſt, as a King, ſhall be Servants of Puniſhment; they ſhall ſerve the Glory of God's Power and Juſtice, in their eternal Miſery and Sufferings.</p>
            <p n="5">5thly, Conſider the Nature and Advanta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges of the Kingdom of Chriſt. There are ſweet Fruits of the Kingdom of Grace, and there are enriching Benefits of the Kingdom of Glory. It was propheſied of Chriſt, as a King, That Men ſhould be bleſſed in him, and Nations ſhould call him Bleſſed. What a Glory is this to Jeſus Chriſt, that Men are bleſſed, and ſhall bleſs themſelves in this King, that ever they were conquered by the Sword of his Word, that ever they were brought under the Scepter of his Grace: They ſhall
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:42338:36"/>rejoyce that ever they were bound with the Cords of his Doctrine, and Laws, and ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jected to the Yoke of his Government. They call their King Bleſſed, that is raiſed above the reach and rage of all his Enemies, and is now victorious and triumphant over them; that reigns ſo righteouſly, ſo peaceably, ſo proſperouſly; that dethrones Sin and Satan, and inthrones God in the Souls of Men; that preſerves his People from ſinking into an extremity of Miſery, and exalts them to poſſeſs an eternal Felicity. They call him Bleſſed, that hath all Power in Heaven and Earth given to him, and that hath the Key of Hell and Death, <hi>Matth.</hi> 28.18. <hi>Rev.</hi> 1.18. that hath ſuch an unbounded Empirt, and ſo large, and ſuch an extenſive King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom; hath power over all Fleſh, that he might give eternal Life to as many as the Father hath given him, <hi>John</hi> 17.2. and is made Head over all things to the Church, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 1.22. that nothing may hinder the Salvation, or obſtruct the Happineſs, but all things may promote the Good and Welfare of the Church.</p>
            <p n="1">1ſt. Conſider who Jeſus Chriſt is: He <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> God's Righteous Servant, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 53.11. and he Well-beloved Son, <hi>Matth.</hi> 3.17. Is it not better to be in the Kingdom of God's Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Servant, than to be under the power of a wicked, hardned, obſtinate Rebel? Is it not more deſireable to be tranſlated into the
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:42338:36"/>Kingdom of God's dear Son, <hi>Col.</hi> 1.13. than to be at the beck and command of God's bitter Enemy, and implacable Adverſary? Chriſt, the Son of God by nature, grants the Privilege of Adoption to all his Subjects, <hi>John</hi> 1.12. This is ſuch a Mercy, as no Son of an earthly King vouchſafes to his Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects.</p>
            <p n="2">2dly, Jeſus Chriſt reigns to do Right to God, and to eſtabliſh his Throne in the Souls of Men. He was deſigned to raiſe up thoſe that fell off from God, and ſunk into Ruine, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 49.6. Chriſt is God's Servant to raiſe up the Tribes of <hi>Jacob,</hi> and to bring back thoſe that were gone aſtray from God, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 49.5. and to reſtore ſuch as were alie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nated from God, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 49.6. Chriſt retrieves, recovers God's Right; he eſtabliſhes his own Throne by Juſtice and Judgment, <hi>Iſaiah</hi> 9.7. and he is ſaid to execute Juſtice and Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment in the Earth, <hi>Jer.</hi> 23.5. Chriſt exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cutes Juſtice, in reſtoring and giving back to God that which is his own: and he executes Judgment in deſtroying Satan's Works and Luſts, 1 <hi>John</hi> 3.8. in mortiſying the vile Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections of Sinners. This was one great Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefit of the Jubilee, that the Servant returned to his Family, <hi>Levit.</hi> 25.10. He that was a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lienated from his Father, and ſerved Stran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers, now returned to do his Duty, and ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered Obedience to his Parents: Even ſo Jeſus Chriſt reſtores Men to God's Family, and
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:42338:37"/>grants unto them, as a great Favour and Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vilege, that they may ſerve him without ſla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſh Fear of Deſtruction, in Holineſs and Righteouſneſs all the Days of their Lives, <hi>Luke</hi> 1.74, 75. Yea Chriſt reſtores the Creatures unto God: The Subjects of Chriſt uſe them purely; they did not feed and fuel their Luſts with them, but receive them with thankſgiving, as their Father's Goods, and Gifts, and uſe them to ſtrengthen and ſupport them in the Lord's Work and Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice. It is a great perverting, abuſing, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlaving the Creatures, when they victual Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tan's Garriſons, and feed his Soldiers: But then the Creatures are reſcued from Bondage, when they nouriſh God's Prieſts, and feed his Worſhippers.</p>
            <p n="3">3dly, Thoſe that are in Chriſt's King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom are nearly related to him, and to each other.</p>
            <p n="1">1. They are nearly related to Chriſt: They are his Seed and Children, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 53.10. <hi>He ſhall ſee his ſeed. — Behold, I and the Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, whom God hath given me,</hi> Iſa. 8.18. Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus, as a ſecond <hi>Adam,</hi> as an everlaſting Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, begets them, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 9.6. He is made Sanctification to them, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.30. They re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive of his fulneſs, Grace for Grace, <hi>J<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>s</hi> 1.16. They are Chriſt's Brethren, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 22.22. <hi>I will declare thy name unto my brethren He is not aſhamed to call them Brethren,</hi> Hebr. 2.11. They are the Lamb's Wife, <hi>Rev.</hi> 19.7.
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:42338:37"/>They are the Members of Chriſt, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 5.30. <hi>We are members of his body, of his fleſh, and of his bone.</hi> As <hi>Eve</hi> was taken out of <hi>Adam,</hi> as to her human Nature, ſo we are taken out of Chriſt, as to our new and divine Nature. Water and Blood came out of Chriſt's Side, <hi>John</hi> 19.34. The Blood of Chriſt is the meritorious Cauſe of our new State of Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtification, and the Water ſignified the Spirit that gives a new Nature in Sanctification. And how Honourable is it for Subjects to be ſo nearly related to the King of Glory? And how ſweet, eaſie, and gentle, is Chriſt's Government over his Children, over his Brethren, over his Spouſe and Members? Surely Chriſt will not carry a hard, a heavy, a rigorous Hand over thoſe that are ſo near and dear to him: <hi>He ſhall ſpare the poor and needy,</hi> Pſal. 72.13. And, as a Shepherd, <hi>ſhall gather the lambs with his arm, and carry them in his boſom, and gently lead thoſe that are with young,</hi> Iſa. 40.11. Was there ever ſuch an Honour put on a Flock, as that they ſhould be Members, and Brethren, and Children of the Shepherd.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Chriſt's Subjects are nearly related to each other; and this is a moſt ſweet Truth, as well as a great Myſtery: They are not only Fellow-Servants in the ſame Houſe, and Fellow-Citizens in the ſame City of God; but they are Brethren in the ſame Family, and Members of the ſame Body, and anima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted,
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:42338:38"/>or influenced, and acted by the ſame Spirit, and therefore have the greateſt Obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gations laid on them to love each other, to ſeek one another's Good, and promote one anothers Welfare. Shall Brethren claſh with one another, or Members fight againſt each other? He that for Chriſt's ſake is hated of his Father, Mother, Brethren, Siſters, he doth, by virtue of his Intereſt and Union with Chriſt, recover a hundred fold more Kindred and Relations: Elder Chriſtians are as his Fathers and Mothers, younger Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians are his Brothers and Siſters, <hi>Mark</hi> 10.29, 30. yea as his Children to ſerve and che<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh him. O what a bleſſed Kingdom is this! when the Subjects are ſo endeared to each other, that they have not only ſold their Lands to relieve their ſpiritual Brethren, <hi>Acts</hi> 2.4, 5. <hi>Acts</hi> 4.34. but have alſo jeo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parded, and hazarded their Lives, to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve the Lives of their Holy Kindred, <hi>Rom.</hi> 16.3, 4. <hi>Aquilla</hi> and <hi>Priſcilla</hi> laid down their Necks, expoſed themſelves to the greateſt Dangers, to preſerve the Life of <hi>Paul: Rahab</hi> ventured her own Life, to preſerve the Spies that were the People of God, <hi>Joſhua</hi> 2.15.</p>
            <p n="4">4thly, If we conſider the great Benefits that we receive from Chriſt's Kingdom.</p>
            <p n="1">1. He heals, waſhes, refines, anoints, his Subjects. A Governour is called a Healer, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 3.6, 7. Jeſus Chriſt, as a King, is a Healer, a Phyſician to his whole Kingdom,
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:42338:38"/>and to all his Subjects, <hi>Matth.</hi> 9.12. Our Souls are diſeaſed, weak, feeble, ruined; and woe be to us if this Ruine be not under Chriſt's Hand! Never was there ſuch a Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſician that dy'd to provide a Remedy to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cover and reſtore his Patients: By his Stripes we are healed, yea by his Death we live, If a King, that is but a political Head, be the Breath of his Subjects Noſtrils, <hi>Lam.</hi> 4.20. much more is Chriſt the Breath of our No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrils; as he is a natural Head that gives Life, and continual influences of Grace.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Jeſus Chriſt waſhes, <hi>John</hi> 13.8. <hi>Except I waſh thee, thou haſt no part with me;</hi> that is, in the eternal Inheritance in the Kingdom of Glory. None waſhes ſo powerfully as Chriſt; he can waſh away a Backſliding, Revolting, Rebellious, Whoriſh Heart; he can waſh away our Spiritual Leproſie, and Plague-Sores; he can waſh our Aethiopian Skin, and our Leopard Spots, <hi>Jer.</hi> 13.23.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Jeſus Chriſt Refines, <hi>Mal.</hi> 3.23 and there is no ſuch Refiner as Chriſt, no ſuch refining ſire as Chriſt's is. A Refiner, or his Fire, cannot change Iron, Braſs, Tin, or Lead, into Gold and Silver; but Chriſt, by ſeparating our Droſs from us, renders us precious, and makes us Veſſels of Gold and Silver, 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.20.</p>
            <p n="4">4. Jeſus Chriſt anoints his Subjects, <hi>Ezek.</hi> 16.9. <hi>And I anointed thee with Oil.</hi> This is an Alluſion to the ſweet-ſmelling Oils, that Perſons were purfiied with, <hi>Eſther</hi> 2.12. The
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:42338:39"/>Graces of Chriſt's Spirit are fragrant, and cauſe us to ſmell ſweet in the Noſtrils of God and Man. Saints are called Chriſtians, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they partake of Chriſt's Ointment, 1 <hi>John</hi> 2.20, 27. You have an unction from the Holy One, that is, from Chriſt: As the Mediator is anointed himſelf, ſo he is ſtyled Chriſt, and as we are anointed by this Anoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, ſo we are called Chriſtians: And this is peculiar to Chriſt's Subjects, that they are all anointed, and partake even of the unction of their King. If we have not the unction of the Spirit of Chriſt, he will not own us to be Subjects in his Kingdom; or to be Members of his Body: <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.9. <hi>If a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> man have not the ſpirit of Chriſt, he is none of his.</hi> Chriſt's Unction doth puriſie us from Sin, conſecrate us to God, teach us the ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blime Truths, and wonderful Myſteries of the Kingdom of God, 1 <hi>John</hi> 2.20.27. The Prophets were anointed, 1 <hi>Kings</hi> 19.16. and they, by the unction of the Holy Ghoſt, were Seers, 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 9.9. They did ſee ſar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and know more than others. From hence I conceive the Phraſe is borrowed, That the anointing teacheth us; and Chriſt, by anointing us, fits and exalts us to be ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual Kings, <hi>Rev.</hi> 1.5, 6. He <hi>hath made in Kings.</hi> Saints do command and rule their own Spiri's govern their Thoughts, order and bound their Affections, curb, reſtrain,
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:42338:39"/>and keep under their Paſſions; and, as of old, Wreſtlers were anointed,
<note n="*" place="margin">Fabius Agoniſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>con.</note> that the Hand of the Adverſary might ſlip off from them, and take no faſt ſure hold of them, to throw them; ſo Chriſt by anointing us with his Spirit, Satan is defeated, he is diſappointed, he cannot faſten on us, and have Advantages againſt us; firſt to throw our Minds to the Earth, and then to caſt our Souls to Hell.</p>
            <p n="2">2dly, In Chriſt's Kingdom, we have Reſt, <hi>Matth.</hi> 8.11. <hi>Many ſhall come from the eaſt and weſt, and ſit down with Abraham, Iſaac, and Jacob, in the Kingdom of God.</hi> Souls tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vel up and down, traverſe the Earth to and fro, diſquiet themſelves in vain, and weary themſelves to no purpoſe; they never come to ſit down till they preſs and get into the Kingdom of God, and here is a moſt ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable reſt to ſit in the Throne with Chriſt, <hi>Rev.</hi> 3.21.</p>
            <p n="3">3dly. In Chriſt's Kingdom is a Feaſt; but in Satan's Kigndom Souls famiſh, ſtarve and periſh with thirſt, <hi>Luke</hi> 22.29, 30. <hi>that you eat and drink at my table, in my Kingdom.</hi> God makes a Feaſt in his Holy Mountain, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 25.6. Saints have the firſt Courſe in this World, and ſo it is a Dinner, <hi>Matth.</hi> 22.4. they ſhall enjoy the ſecond and third Courſes in Heaven; and ſo it is <hi>the Marriage-Supper of the Lamb,</hi> Rev. 19.9. Did ever any Shepherd feed his Flock with his own fleſh and blood?
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:42338:40"/>Is there any that is a Paſtor, and a Paſture too? yet ſo is it here, <hi>John</hi> 6.53, 54, 55, 56, 57. we here eat the fleſh, and drink the bloud of the Son of Man in this Life; and in Heaven to all Eternity we ſhall feed on the delicious Fruits of Chriſt, <hi>the Tree of Life,</hi> Rev. 2.7.</p>
            <p n="4">4thly, In Chriſt's Kingdom is Liberty, <hi>John</hi> 8.36. <hi>If the Son doth make you free, th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> you ſhall be free indeed.</hi> Chriſt reigns to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy the reigning Power of Sin and Satan, to caſt the Prince of this World out of his Throne and Kingdom, <hi>John</hi> 12.31. <hi>N<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> ſhall the Prince of this World be caſt out.</hi> Chriſt reigns to tumble down the God of this World from his Heaven, <hi>Luke</hi> 10.18. <hi>Iſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> Satan falling as Lightning from Heaven</hi> Chriſt breaks this oppreſſour to pieces, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 72.4<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> he burſts the Yoke of Sin, ſnaps in ſunder the Snares of Satan, and delivers from the bondage of Corruption.</p>
            <p n="5">5thly, In Chriſt's Kingdom is ſafety. This great Shepherd keeps his Sheep, and watch<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> over his Flock in this Night of Time, in this Wilderneſs of the World, <hi>John</hi> 17.1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>While I was with them in the World, I kept the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> in thy Name, and none of them is loſt.</hi> Saines are ſaid to be preſerved in Chriſt Jeſus <hi>Jude</hi> 1. Chriſt guards his Flock, and is <hi>a wall of fire round about them,</hi> Zech. 2.5. no Lion ſhall be there, nor any ravences Beaſt ſhall go up thereon, it ſhall not be
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:42338:40"/>found there: but the Redeemed ſhall walk there. Satan, that roaring Lion, ſhall not prey on Chriſt's Lambs, or Sheep; they ſhall be as ſafe, as if there were no Beaſts of Prey about them; <hi>they ſhall lye down ſafely in the wilderneſs, and ſleep ſecurely in the woods,</hi> Ezek. 34.25. Satan ſhall not be there to hurt them, becauſe their Shepherd is ſtill with them to ſave them, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 23.4. <hi>Thou art with me in the Valley of the Shadow of Death; I will fear no evil, thy rod and thy ſtaff they comfort me continually.</hi> As <hi>David,</hi> when a Shepherd, did fight with a Lion and Bear, and ſlew them, to reſcue a poor Lamb of his Flock, 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 17.34, 35, 36. ſo Chriſt did once in his own Perſon encounter with, and deſtroy Satan, <hi>Heb.</hi> 2.15. and he doth by his Spirit and Grace in his Members, daily ſight with him, and foil him, 1 <hi>John</hi> 2.14. <hi>ye are ſtrong and have overcome the wicked one.</hi> Chriſt ſtands, feeds and keeps his Flock <hi>in the ſtrength of the Lord,</hi> Micah 5.4. and ſo this one Shepherd is ſtronger than all the Beaſts of Prey, whether they be wicked Men, or evil Spirits: as he is omniſcient he underſtands all the difficulties and dangers of his Sheep; and as he is omnipotent, he can reſcue, ſave, and preſerve them. Tho' this great Shepherd hath a numerous Flock ſcattered through the World, yet he knows all his Sheep, and doth hear all their Cries and Prayers, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 72.12, 14. <hi>He ſhall deliver
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:42338:41"/>the needy when he crieth: the poor alſo, and hi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> that hath no helper. He ſhall redeem their S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> from deceit and violence, and precious ſhall they blood be in his ſight.</hi> Spiritual Enemies <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> attempt againſt the People of God, by P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licy or Power; yet Chriſt fruſtrates the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Adverſaries in both: he redeems the Souls <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> his People both from Fraud and Violence no earthly King can know every Subject<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> or hear the Cries and Petitions of all that are oppreſſed.</p>
            <p n="5">5thly, Jeſus Chriſt ſtrengthens and en<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles his True Subjects to obey him, as Chr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap> dwells in their Hearts by Faith, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 3.17. ſo he ſtrengthens his People, <hi>Phil.</hi> 4.13. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>can do all things through Chriſt that ſtreng<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="4 letters">
                     <desc>••••</desc>
                  </gap> me. I will put my Spirit into them, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> them to walk in my ſtatutes,</hi> Ezek. 36.2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Chriſt gives Influences, Aids, and Aſſiſtan<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> for every Act of Obedience, becauſe he is <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> a Natural Head that communicates Sp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap> to his Subjects, as Members, and as a Ro<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> that derives Sap to all his Branches. T<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> Subjects of Earthly Kings have no ſuch nee<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> of them, or dependance on them, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> ſtrength to yield them Obedience. But i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> was propheſied of Chriſt, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 72.6. <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> ſhall come down like rain on the mowen gr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> as ſhowers that water the Earth.</hi> This Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture teaches us how great a Dependance Chriſt's Subjects have on him, and how pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious a Benefit they receive by him; the
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:42338:41"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>owen Graſs cannot ſpring and grow with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>t Rain from Heaven: ſo Chriſt's Subjects cannot ſpring up in Holineſs, or bring forth any Fruits of Righteouſneſs, except they have a Rain of Influences, a Shower of gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious Communication from the Lord Jeſus Chriſt. Every Subject of Chriſt is a dry ground, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 42.3. and needs watering from that River, yea from that Fountain of Grace that is above in Chriſt. We cannot take one ſtep in the way towards a Bleſſed Eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity, but leaning on Chriſt, <hi>Cant.</hi> 8.5. the Church <hi>cometh up out of the wilderneſs,</hi> and travels towards the Heavenly <hi>Canaan, lean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing on her beloved. Ezek.</hi> 45.17. the King there ſpoken of, was to provide and prepare all Sacrifices, as Burnt-Offerings, Sin-Offe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rings, and Thank-Offerings, for the People his Subjects. By this King I underſtand Chriſt, as he did give himſelf for us, <hi>a Lamb for a burnt-offering,</hi> John 1.29. <hi>as a ſin-offe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring,</hi> 2 Cor. 5.21. ſo he furniſhes us with Thank-Offerings, he kindles Love in our Hearts by his own Beams, he circumciſes our Hearts, <hi>Col.</hi> 2.11. cuts off the filthy fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>skin of ſinful, inordinate Self-love, that did hinder and intercept our Love to God, and it is by vertue of our Marriage-Union with him, that we bring forth Fruits to God, <hi>Rom.</hi> 7.4. all <hi>the fruits of righteouſneſs are by Jeſus Chriſt to the praiſe and glory of God,</hi> Phil. 1.11.</p>
            <pb n="78" facs="tcp:42338:42"/>
            <p n="6">6thly, Jeſus Chriſt receives the Souls of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> Subjects at laſt; as he committed his ow<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Soul at death, to the hands of the Father <hi>Luke</hi> 23.46. ſo now he hath merited and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained this Honour to be the Receiver a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> Guardian of departing Souls, <hi>Acts</hi> 7.5<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Stephen</hi> called upon God, ſaying, <hi>Lord Je<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> receive my Spirit:</hi> he called upon God, t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> it was through Chriſt the Mediator; God would not receive, but reject, and ab<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap> our Spirits, were they not joined to, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> accepted in, and had acceſs to him thro<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap> Chriſt: Oh how deſirable a King is Je<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> Chriſt, that will be a Friend to us, when <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> forſake us, or can do nothing for our So<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>s Oh what a Truſt doth Jeſus Chriſt undert<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>e, to keep departed Souls till the laſt day, and then reſtore them to glorious Bodies. O<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> departing Souls muſt fall into the hands <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> an angry Sin-revenging God, were the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> not ſuch a gracious King in whoſe Hand we might depoſite and truſt them.</p>
            <p n="7">7thly, Jeſus Chriſt is ſuch a King that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> conquer and deſtroy Death, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> he threatens it, <hi>Hoſ.</hi> 13.14. <hi>O death I will <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> thy plague:</hi> O <hi>grave I will be thy destruction</hi> here is a promiſe in the Verſe to the Sain<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s <hi>I will ranſom them from the power of the gr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> I will redeem them from death:</hi> and this pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe is joined with a threatning againſt Dear<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> and the Grave. How wonderful, ho<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> great and mighty a King is Jeſus Chriſt, that
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:42338:42"/>threatens ſo powerful and victorious a King as Death is! How long hath Death reigned, and how large an Empire hath it had in the World! it is ſaid <hi>Rom.</hi> 5.14. <hi>Death reigned from Adam to Moſes;</hi> yea, we may extend the duration of its Kingdom further; it hath reigned from the Fall of the firſt <hi>Adam</hi> to this day; and how many conquered Subjects hath it had? 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15.22. <hi>in Adam all died.</hi> Death is ſuch a King as ſhakes its Black Rod over, and brandiſhes it's ſharp and glittering Sword againſt the whole World; it hath threatned, arreſted, and cut off the Great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt Kings and Conquerors; it hath been ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Terrible to them that by Oppreſſion, Vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence, and Cruelty, cauſed their Terrour in the Land of the Living, <hi>Ezek.</hi> 32.23. none of the Kings of the World can prevent the Fatal ſtroke of Death on themſelves, much leſs can they divert it from their Subjects: but Chriſt is ſuch a King as combates with Death, and overcomes it; he taſted Death indeed himſelf once, <hi>Heb.</hi> 2.9. but it was to aboliſh it, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.10. he became a Subject to it for a time, that he might ſwallow it up for ever, and be a Lord over the dead to raiſe them up, <hi>Rom.</hi> 14.9. and reſcue them from this Enemy. And how ſtrong, yet how ſweet are theſe Words of Chriſt, <hi>I will be the plague of death;</hi> I will be a Diſcaſe, yea, a mortal Diſeaſe to kill Death it ſelf: and, <hi>Grave, I will be thy deſtruction.</hi> Chriſt
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:42338:43"/>fulfills his threatning, when he ſeeks out the Duſt of his People, and forms it up into a Body: this defeats and diſanuls the Victory of the Grave, that it may be ſaid, O <hi>Grave<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> where is thy victory?</hi> though thou didſt cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupt, putreſie, and diſſolve our Bodies, th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> thou didſt devour our Fleſh and crumble it into Duſt, and take away the very ſhape of a Body, yet we have new Bodies formed and organized again, and when theſe Bodies ſhall receive their Souls, and be quickened by them, then it may be ſaid, <hi>O death, where is thy ſting?</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15.55. What ha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> thou gotten by ſtinging and killing our Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies? behold, they are alive again! The<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e is a Day when the Lord will make up<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> Jewels, <hi>Malachy</hi> 3.17. And then God's Jew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>els are made up, when immortal Souls ſhall be joined to, and ſet in the Rings of Glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious Bodies. Chriſt is ſuch a King as will conform all his Subjects to himſelf, both is Soul and Body: When he regenerates the Soul, then it bears the Image of the ſecond <hi>Adam;</hi> when he raiſes the Body, this is <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s proper Regeneration to be begotten, and born from the dead, as Chriſt was, <hi>Col.</hi> 1.1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>. <hi>Revel.</hi> 1.5. When old <hi>Adam</hi>'s Tenour is out, and quite aboliſhed; when Chriſt, b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> his Spirit, quickens the Body, <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.11. then it bears the Image of the Heavenly <hi>Adam,</hi> and is held of him, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15.49. Saints are the Children of God, as they are
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:42338:43"/>the Children of the Reſurrection, <hi>Luke</hi> 20.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>6. This is a new Ground, and Reaſon, why they ſhould be called the Children of God, the Seed of Chriſt. When Saints a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wake out of the Duſt, they ſhall be ſatisfied with God's likeneſs, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 17.15. When they are begotten again into a lively Hope, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.3, 4. they bear God's Image in their Souls; but when they ſhall be raiſed, or be begot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten from the dead, then they ſhall alſo bear Chriſt's Image in their Bodies, and ſo ſhall be ſatisfied with the Image of Chriſt as an Everlaſting Father. O what a precious Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by! What an incomparable Priviledge is this! that Jeſus Chriſt will not forget or re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject our Duſt for ever, but ſeek it out, and form it up as an Habitation for our Souls, and an everlaſting Temple for his Spirit to dwell in.</p>
            <p n="8">8thly, Jeſus Chriſt is ſuch a King, as will gather and draw up all his ſincere Subjects to him, to be with him for ever, 1 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 4.17. As he receives their Souls in a dying Hour, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 49.15. <hi>Acts.</hi> 7.59. ſo he will come again to revive their Bodies, and then he will receive their whole Man to himſelf, <hi>John.</hi> 14.3. What wonderful Grace and Kindneſs is this, that where the Maſter is, there the Servant ſhall alſo be, <hi>John</hi> 12.20. That the Sheep ſhall for ever dwell with the great Shepherd, and all the Subjects of this Glorious King ſhall abide with him, and ſee
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:42338:44"/>his Glory, ſo as to ſhare in it, and partake of it, <hi>John</hi> 17.24. 2 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 2.14. Chriſt, the King, is the Harbinger and Forerunner of his Subjects, <hi>Hebr.</hi> 6.20. He is gone in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to another World to chooſe an Eternal Inhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritance for his Brethren, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 47.4. He ſhall chooſe our Inheritance for us: And Chriſt, by interceeding with his Father, that his People may be with him, doth prepare a Place for them, <hi>John</hi> 17.24. <hi>John</hi> 14.2, 3. Chriſt's Interceſſion is ſo powerful, that it cannot be deny'd.</p>
            <p>I would now give you ſome Counſels and Directions, that you may ſtay and contin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e in this Kingdom, and not be gathered <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> of it, and deprived of the Bleſſedneſs and Glory of it.</p>
            <p n="1">1ſt. O come forth and ſee King <hi>Solom<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>,</hi> Cant. 3.11. This King <hi>Solomon</hi> is King <hi>Jeſus;</hi> he hath made him a rich and glori<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> Chariot to ride forth in, and to viſit King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doms, Nations, and People. The Goſpel as preached in the World is the Spiritu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> Chariot, that Chriſt ſits in, and the wh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> Horſe he rides on, <hi>Rev.</hi> 6.2. The Church in her Miniſters may be, and is compar<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> to the Horſes in <hi>Pharaoh</hi>'s Chariot, <hi>Cant</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>.9. The Church, by her Miniſters, do's dr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> Jeſus Chriſt about the World. O conſider this, the Goſpel is not fixed to one Nation; the Chariot of Chriſt is moving, and may
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:42338:44"/>quickly paſs by us and be gone from us. It is a great Mercy, that Chriſt's Chariots come to us, that he appears among us. O ſlight not the Opportunity; neglect not the Day of Grace: Come ſorth from your Ignorance and Night of Darkneſs; come forth from your ſlight, low, and contemptible Thoughts of Chriſt: O fix the Eye of your Minds on him, look with a ſteady Eye on Chriſt, <hi>John</hi> 6.40. <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, We ſhould contemplate the Son, our Minds ſhould dwell on him; we ſhould not content our ſelves with ſeldom and tranſient Glances on Chriſt, but our Thoughts ſhould be converſant about Chriſt. Do we not need Chriſt? Is he not abſolutely neceſſary for us? Muſt we not wander, if Chriſt doth not guide us, and fall if he doth not ſupport us; and be a Prey to Satan, if he doth not guard and protect us? Muſt we not famiſh, if he doth not feed us; and periſh, if he doth not fold us? And be Friendleſs and Harbourleſs at laſt, if he doth not receive us? How will you look Death, or the Judge in the Face, if you do not firſt ſee Chriſt, and his Salvati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on? O view, and look well on Chriſt. Is there any thing in him to be diſliked, to be excepted againſt? Is he not altogether lovely, <hi>Cant.</hi> 5.16. Whatever is deſireable, all meets in Jeſus Chriſt, and there is nothing in him but what is lovely; what may kindle Love, draw Hearts, captivate Souls. If you
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:42338:45"/>diſlike any thing in Chriſt, if you harbour any Prejudice, cheriſh any Objection againſt him, it is becauſe Satan hath blinded your Minds, and caſt a Veil over your Hearts, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4.4, 5.</p>
            <p n="2">2dly, O run to Jeſus Chriſt: <hi>Iſa.</hi> 55.5. <hi>Th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> ſhalt call a nation thou knoweſt not, and people that knew not thee, ſhall run unto thee, becauſe of the Lord thy God; becauſe of the holy one of Iſrael that hath glorified thee.</hi> O will you not run to him who is the Seat of Beauty, the Fountain of Honour, the Treaſury of all ſpiritual Riches, the Subject and Centre of Life? Will you not run to the Captain, the Author, the Wells of Salvation? <hi>Hebr.</hi> 2.10. <hi>Hebr.</hi> 5.9. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 12.3. O will you not fly from Sin, Satan, and Eternal Death, by running to Chriſt? Is there any ſhadow from ſcorching Heat, but Chriſt's? <hi>Cant.</hi> 2.2. Any Wing to cover you from Birds of Prey, but his? <hi>Pſal.</hi> 36.7. Any Fold to protect you from Beaſts of Prey, b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> Chriſt's Fold? <hi>John</hi> 10.9. <hi>He that enters by me</hi> (that is into the Fold) <hi>ſhall be ſaved.</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> Sinners can give no Reaſon why they wil<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Dye, <hi>Ezek.</hi> 18.31. ſurely they can give <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Reaſon, why they ſhould not run to Jeſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> Chriſt. That Text, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 55.5. affords co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent Arguments, mighty Reaſons why we ſhould run to him.</p>
            <p n="1">1. God is his God: If ever we would have any comfortable Knowledge of God,
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:42338:45"/>any honourable Relation to God, any ſweet Communion with God, we muſt run to Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt. God is only to be found, and enjoyed in Chriſt. Will you cut your ſelves off? Will you eſtrange your ſelves for ever from God? Will he not be a ſatisfying and an everlaſting Portion, when all other Comforts fail, all other Friends forſake, all our Lamps are put out?</p>
            <p n="2">2. God the Father hath glorified him: He hath exalted him. And ſhall we de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs, debaſe him, and keep him ſtill in a ſtate of Humiliation? Hath the Father gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven him a Throne in Heaven; and ſhall we deny him one in our Hearts? Are Angels, Principalities, and Powers made ſubject to him, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3.32. and ſhall we lift up our ſelves againſt him? Do the nobleſt Creatures worſhip at his Footſtool, and execute his Commands; and ſhall we reject his Yoke, affront his Authority, and trample his Laws under our Feet? Is Chriſt glorified; and will you deſpiſe and ſlight him? Is not a glorified Redeemer worthy of our Love, Praiſe, and Obedience? Shall vile and dunghil Objects draw away our Affections, and a glorified Saviour be denied our Hearts? Would we not commend our Spirits to him at laſt, and ſhall we not give our Hearts to him now, <hi>Prov.</hi> 23.26. Shall our laſt Act be our firſt Gift to Jeſus Chriſt? Wilt thou commend thy Soul to Chriſt only, when
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:42338:46"/>thou canſt keep it no longer in the Body? Is it not dreadful for a Glorified Chriſt with his Omnipotent Arm to fall on thee for De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction? Is it not deſirable that a Glorified Chriſt by his Almighty Power ſhould draw thee up to him for Salvation?</p>
            <p n="3">3. <hi>Kiſs the Son,</hi> Pſal. 2. laſt. this is a ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual Act of Homage, 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 10.1. <hi>Samuel</hi> did anoint and kiſs <hi>Saul,</hi> thereby recogni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zing his Authority, and obliging himſelf to Obedience and Subjection to him, as his So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vereign: The Promiſe is the Mouth of Chriſt, and Faith is the Mouth of the Soul, and when the Mouth of Faith is applied to the Mouth of Chriſt in the Promiſe, then we give Chriſt a ſpiritual Kiſs; when Chriſt ſpeaks, and offers himſelf, we ſhould come in with our Amen of Faith, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.20. to the word of him who is <hi>the Amen, and the faithful wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs,</hi> Rev. 3.14. our Obedience and Subje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction to Chriſt ſhould not be ſeigned, or for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced, but begin in a faithful and loving Kiſs to him that is Love it ſelf, <hi>Cant.</hi> 3.5. when Chriſt applies his Words and Promiſes of Grace to us, then he kiſſes us with the kiſſes of his Mouth, <hi>Cant.</hi> 1.2. when we apply our Mouth of Faith to Chriſt's Word of Grace, when we ſincerely declare our Aſſent and Conſent to it, then we kiſs Chriſt.</p>
            <p n="4">4. We muſt preſs into the Kingdom of Chriſt, as it were force a Paſſage into it, and <hi>take it by violence, Luke</hi> 16.16. Matth. 11.12.
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:42338:46"/>we muſt have a Room, a Place in Chriſt's Kingdom, he muſt reign over us, or elſe Sin, Death, and the Devil, will reign over us: We muſt enter into Chriſt's Palace, or be ſhut up in his Priſon: we muſt preſs into Chriſt's Kingdom, that we may avoid a fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture eternal Storm of Vengeance. Thoſe that are hungry and famiſhing, will force in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to a place where there is Plenty of Bread. Poor neceſſitious Soldiers will ſtorm, will break into a rich City with the hazard of their Lives, and ſhall we not be urgent to get into Chriſt's Kingdom, where there is a Royal Feaſt, a ſweet Reſt, unſearchable and eternal Riches? if you are not Chriſt's, you will be Satan's. Do you not fear to ſee God's frowning face, to feel his puniſhing hand, to drop into the bottomleſs Pit, to be caſt into the Lake that burns with Fire and Brimſtone for ever. Be not cold or in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>different whether you get into Chriſts's King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom or no. Do not content your ſelves with looſe hopes, ungrounded and preſumptuous Confidences, lukewarm and lazy Endeavours. It is ſaid, the Gentiles ſhould fall down to the Church, and make Supplication to her, that is to prevail with her, to be admitted and received by her into the Kingdom of Chriſt, it is further foretold, <hi>Zech.</hi> 8. laſt, <hi>That ten men of all Languages of the Nations ſhould take hold of the skirt of him that is a
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:42338:47"/>Jew,</hi> and ſo is a True Believer and a ſpiritual Worſhipper, <hi>and ſay, we will go with you, for we have heard that God is with you.</hi> They would not be put by, they would not be ſhaken or caſt off, they reſolved they would join them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves to the Church of God, and not be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluded, kept, or thruſt out. It is ſaid, <hi>the Gentiles ſhould flow as waters to God's Holy Moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain,</hi> Iſ. 2.23. <hi>and ſhould fly as clouds, and as doves to their windows,</hi> Iſa 60.8. this expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes ſerious, earneſt, and ſpiritual Violence.</p>
            <p n="5">5. That you may be thus Earneſt, you muſt deſire Chriſt to caſt chains of Light, and Love about you; to ſubdue, conquer, and overcome you, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 45.14. it is promiſed that the Gentiles ſhould come over, a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> come after the Church in Chains. Chriſt muſt faſten thoſe Chains on, and about the Souls of Sinners, and draw them that they may run after him, <hi>Cant.</hi> 1.4. though Chriſt's Name be <hi>as a fragrant Ointment,</hi> Cant. 1.3. <hi>as a strong perfume,</hi> though there be a draw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Beauty, Excellency, Treaſure, Love, in Chriſt, yet all theſe will not prevail without an Almighty and drawing Arm, ſuch is out averſeneſs and perverſeneſs. It is propheſied of Chriſt, That he ſhould ſubdue the Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples and the Nations under the Feet of the Church, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 47.3. ſo that they ſhall bow at the Feet of the Church, and worſhip God at her Feet as her Diſciples and Children, <hi>Revel.</hi> 3.9. And we cannot be ſubdued to
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:42338:47"/>Chriſt, if our Iniquities are not ſubdued, <hi>Micah</hi> 7.19. Chriſt cannot rule over us, if Sin do reign in us; the Law of Chriſt, and the Law of Sin are contrary and incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtent.</p>
            <p n="6">6. We muſt openly own and avow Chriſt, and moſt ſtrongly engage our ſelves to him. 1. We muſt openly own, confeſs, and avow Chriſt. It is propheſied of <hi>Egypt,</hi> That there ſhould be an Altar to the Lord in the midſt of the Land, and alſo a Pillar at the Border, to declare to all, That <hi>Egypt</hi> was converted to, and become a Worſhipper of the Lord, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 19.19. Thoſe that ſtood with the Lamb on Mount <hi>Zion,</hi> had their Father's Name written in their Forehead, <hi>Rev.</hi> 14.1. <hi>Cyprian</hi> ſaith, That when Chriſtians were apprehended, they did not deny, but con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs'd themſelves Chriſtians, always to the danger, and ſometimes to the loſs of their Lives. 2. We muſt moſt ſolemnly and ſtrongly engage our ſelves to the Lord. It is ſaid, That the Egyptians ſhould ſwear to the Lord, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 19.18. and ſo as it were take an Oath of ſpiritual Allegiance to Chriſt, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 119.106. <hi>I have ſworn, and I will per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form it, that I will keep thy righteous judgments.</hi> Another remarkable Expreſſion we find, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 44.5. <hi>One ſhall ſay, I am the Lord's, another ſhall ſubſcribe with his hand to the Lord.</hi> Converts ſhould as it were draw Indentures, and give it under Hand and Seal, That they would
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:42338:48"/>be the Lord's Servants; That they would not ſtart, recoil, or go back from him, <hi>Jer.</hi> 50.4, 5. <hi>Let us join our ſelves to the Lord in a perpetual covenant that ſhall not be forgotten.</hi> As a bought, a redeemed People, they are devoted, and conſecrated as Firſt-fruits to God and the Lamb, never to be alienated, or put to a common uſe any more, <hi>Revel.</hi> 14.4.</p>
            <p n="7">7. We muſt daily grow in Grace, and be adding new Cubits to our ſpiritual Stature, 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.5. The new Creature muſt, as a Tree, ſpread and ſtrike its Roots deeper into our Souls, <hi>Hoſ.</hi> 14.5. The Water that Chriſt gives us, muſt, as a Well, ſpring up higher and higher in our Souls, <hi>John</hi> 4.14. Worldly Men are ſtill coveting more Earthly Treaſure, to add Houſe to Houſe, and to join Field to Field, that they might be plac<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> alone in the Earth, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 5.8. And is the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> not more reaſon, that we ſhould add Grace to Grace, one degree of Grace to another that Chriſt and the new Creature might be placed alone in our Souls, without Riv<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>'ss Competitors, or Enemies. By growth i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Grace, we paſs and get farther into Chriſt's Kingdom, we have an abundant Entrance into it, we preſs even into the very Heart and Centre of Chriſt's Kingdom, and do not ſtay in the Out skirts and Borders of it. God hath promiſed to Chriſt the encreaſe and enlargement of his King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 9.7. with <hi>Zech.</hi> 9.10. And <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="91" facs="tcp:42338:48"/>we reſtrain and ſtraiten the Kingdom of Chriſt? As this Stone grows and fills the Earth without, <hi>Dan.</hi> 2.35. ſo it ſhould increaſe, and ſill the Soul within. It was propheſied of Chriſt, That he ſhould reign and proſper, <hi>Jer.</hi> 23.5. That he ſhould ride forth conquering and to conquer, <hi>Revel.</hi> 6.2. Let theſe Prophe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies be fulfilled in thee; do not ſtint, ſtop, or bound Chriſt's Kingdom in thy Soul.</p>
            <p n="8">8. We muſt be diligent, active, induſtri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Servants: Trade with Chriſt's Talents, improve his Stock, increaſe his Pounds. Our Lord that is gone into a far Country, yet hath diſpoſed his Goods, hath beſtowed Gifts on his Servants, and enjoined every one his Work, <hi>Mark</hi> 13.34. with <hi>Luke</hi> 19.13, 15. Chriſt would have no idle, no lazy, no droneiſh Servant in his Houſe. All theſe Talents and Gifts are beſtowed, that we might act for Chriſt, enlighten, and draw in others to Chriſt, promote and advance his Kingdom, and encreaſe the number of his Subjects. Our Candle of Knowledge ſhould tind and light many other Candles: Our Fire of Love and Zeal, ſhould warm and inflame many others. While the Church gave a Character of Chriſt's Worth, a De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcription of his Beauty, <hi>Cant.</hi> 5.9, 10, 11, 12, 13. the Daughters of <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hended and conceived that he was ſome ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traordinary Perſon; one tranſcendantly Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent, that ſhe had ſuch fervent Love to
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:42338:49"/>him, and did ſo earneſtly enquire after him. And this ſo wrought on them, that their Hearts did burn with deſires after Chriſt, and they would ſeek him with the Church, <hi>Cant.</hi> 6.1. We ſhould ſay as the godly Jews, <hi>Cant.</hi> 8.8. <hi>We have a little ſiſter that hath no breaſts, What ſhall we do</hi> (that is to promote a Marriage between Chriſt and her) <hi>in the day ſhe ſhall be ſpoken for,</hi> and be wooed to be eſpouſed to Chriſt? The Church pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes ſhe would cauſe Chriſt's Name to be remembred in all Generations; that is, by the preaching of the Word, and thereby bringing forth a Holy Seed to continue, and perpetuate Chriſt's Name in the World, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 72.17. <hi>His name ſhall be continued for ever:</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Jinnon</hi> (that is his Name) ſhall have Sons. Thou art concerned in, and bound by this Promiſe: Every true Member of the Church is obliged by it, to do what he can to propogate Chriſt's Intereſt, to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mote his Kingdom, and continue his Name in the World.</p>
            <p n="9">9. We muſt be willing to ſuffer for the Kingdom of God, 2 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 1.5. The Apoſtle <hi>John</hi> joins the Kingdom and Patience of Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt, <hi>Revel.</hi> 1.9. but <hi>Paul</hi> joins the Kingdom and Glory of God, 1 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 2.11. Firſt we muſt paſs through the Kingdom and Patience of Chriſt, before we paſs in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Kingdom and Glory of God. We cannot enter into, and continue in the
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:42338:49"/>Kingdom of Chriſt, but the World will hate and perſecute us: <hi>John</hi> 8.14. <hi>I have given them thy word, and they have received it, and the world hath hated them.</hi> Saints ſuffered ſo freely, ſo willingly, ſo joyfully for the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of Chriſt, that the World was amazed. <hi>Cyprian</hi> tells us, That Chriſtians, when their Enemies offered to apprehend them, they did not reſiſt; when they asked them of their Religion, they did not tell a Lye, or deny their Faith; they took joyfully the ſpoiling of Goods, <hi>Heb.</hi> 10.34. rejoyced that they were counted worthy to be beaten for Chriſt, <hi>Acts</hi> 5.41. If they were to be offer'd up to confirm the Faith of others, and to evidence their own Faith, they did rejoyce, <hi>Phil.</hi> 2.17. They endured exqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſite Torments with ſuch undaunted Courage, and ſuch unrelenting Spirits, that Natural Men would rather have denied things clear by mathematical Demonſtrations, than have expoſed themſelves to ſuch Tortures. As
<note n="*" place="bottom">
                  <hi>In his Preface to his Diſputations on</hi> Thomas Aquinas.</note> 
               <hi>Medina</hi> truly affirms.</p>
            <p n="10">10. You muſt lead Holy Lives your Light muſt ſhine before Men, <hi>Matth.</hi> 5.16. you muſt hold forth the Excellency, Power, and Efficacy of the Word in your Actions, <hi>Phil.</hi> 2.6. when <hi>Paul</hi> had aſſerted his Faith, that he did believe a Reſurrection of the juſt, and
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:42338:50"/>the unjuſt, he preſently declares the Fruit of this Truth, <hi>Acts</hi> 24.15, 16. <hi>In this I exerciſe my ſelf, to keep a Conſcience void of offence both toward God and man:</hi> he did act and practiſe according to this Truth, it had a prevailing Influence on his Heart, a commanding An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority over his Actions; you muſt much converſe with God here, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 139.17. <hi>when I am awake, I am ever with thee:</hi> and how fitly do thoſe Two Expreſſions agree; <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid</hi> was ever with the Lord on Earth, and <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith, Chriſtians ſhould be ever with the Lord in Heaven, 1 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 4.17. there muſt be a walking with God on Earth, <hi>Gen.</hi> 8.24. <hi>Enoch</hi> walked with God, and God took him, and why did God take him, and for what End? was it not to walk with him in Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, <hi>Rev.</hi> 3.4. thoſe that had not defiled their Garments ſhould walk with Chriſt in white, we muſt <hi>ſhine as lights in this world,</hi> Phil. 2.15. that hereafter we may <hi>ſhine a the ſun, in the king dom of</hi> our <hi>Father,</hi> Matth. 13.43. Jeſus Chriſt muſt be glorified in us now, <hi>John</hi> 17.10. <hi>I am glorified in them,</hi> that we may be aſſured he will be glorified and ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mired in us hereafter, 2 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 1.10. when he will be revealed from Heaven, <hi>he will be glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rified in his Saints, and be admired in them the believe.</hi> Chriſtians muſt not be like the Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then Philoſophers. <hi>Athenagoras</hi> in his <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, or Apology for the Chriſtians, charges the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> that they ſought and aimed at <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>,
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:42338:50"/>an Art of Words, but not a Demonſtration of Works; but he ſaith, that Chriſtian Handicrafts-men and Old Women that could not diſcourſe for their Religion, did yet demonſtrate its Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellency in their Works. When they were beaten, they would not ſtrike again; when they were wronged in their Eſtates, they would not go to Law; they would pray for them that perſecuted them, and love thoſe that hated them.</p>
            <p n="11">11. Conſider how great Guilt you will contract, and what hateful and abominable Creatures you will be, if you reject the Word of the Kingdom, and enter not into it. Chriſt bid his Diſciples to ſhake off the Duſt of their Feet againſt ſuch, <hi>Luke</hi> 10.9, 10, 11. for a Teſtimony againſt them. They that refuſe the Goſpel of the Kingdom, and turn away from the King of Glory, are ſuch unclean Creatures, that Chriſt's Miniſters were not to defile themſelves, or their Feet, by carrying away any of their Duſt; but to ſhake it off, and leave it as a witneſs there, that Chriſt's Ambaſſadors had been there, had preached to them, and been rejected by them. This very Duſt ſhould remain with them to teſtifie, and give in Evidence againſt them in the great Day, that they would not open their Ears to Chriſt, ſpeaking in his Miniſters, but obſtinately hardened their Hearts, both againſt the Maſter and the Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants,
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:42338:51"/>againſt the Lord and his Subjects. Taſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> heed therefore, that you reject not him that ſpeaks from Heaven: Be jealous over your own Souls, that you receive not the Doctrine of Grace, the Word of the Kingdom in vain, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6.2. as the Highway, the ſtony, and thorny Ground did. Let Chriſt's Word root in your Hearts, ſhine and reign in your Lives: Do not think to blind your Eyes, ſtupifie your Conſciences, and cheat your own Souls with an outſide Religion. Great was the Sin of <hi>Ananias</hi> and <hi>Saphira,</hi> that preten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded to devote the whole Price, that they ſold their Land for, to the Service of Chriſt and his Church, yet kept back part of it; and ſo lied to God, and tempted the Holy G<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>Acts</hi> 5.3, 9. O do not dare to tread in their Steps: Will you tempt Chriſt and his Spirit, whether they are omniſcient? Or try whe ther you cannot put a Fallacy or Cheat o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> them? Will you make a coſtly and dange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous Experiment, whether they cannot find out your baſe Metal, your counterfeit Coin, your hypocritical Services: Though you pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend to know God, <hi>Hoſ.</hi> 8.2. yet without ſincerity, Chriſt will not approve and know you, <hi>Matth.</hi> 7.23. Let not Chriſt's Word be received only into your Memories, but let Chriſt himſelf be entertained in your Hearts, to order your Affections, and direct your Converſations. If you do not ope<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> to Chriſt your Hearts below, he will not <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> pen to you his Heaven above.</p>
            <pb n="97" facs="tcp:42338:51"/>
            <p n="4">4. <hi>Uſe,</hi> For Caution: Take heed you do not raſhly judge, and haſtily paſs a Cenſure on the Kingdom of Chriſt, and on the Church of God. Turks, Jews, and Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thens, that ſee the looſe and wicked Lives of ſome Chriſtians, do preſently condemn all Chriſtians, as if there were no ſincere Piety, powerful Religion, or Beauty of Holineſs among them; and thereby take an advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage to reproach Chriſt himſelf, and to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flect on his Goſpel, as if it did allow, and he did approve ſuch things: When as Chriſt loveth Righteouſneſs, and hates Iniquity, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 45.67. He forbids all Sin, he diſlikes and abhors all Iniquity, <hi>Matth</hi> 22.10, 11. <hi>Friend, how cameſt thou in hither, not having a wedding-garment.</hi> Chriſt hath ſpoken plainly enough, <hi>Except a man be born again,</hi> unleſs Men repent and be converted, <hi>John</hi> 3.3, 5. <hi>Matth.</hi> 18.3. <hi>they cannot enter into the kingdom of God:</hi> That without Holineſs Men ſhall not ſee God, <hi>Hebr.</hi> 12.14. Theſe Inſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons and warnings of Chriſt are plain, yet many preſume, and thruſt into the Church of God, and give the Lye to Jeſus Chriſt, as if they ſhould live in Glory, though they be dead in Sin; and ſee God, though they are <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>oid, and utterly deſtitute of Holineſs. But <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ere will ſhortly be an end of all their Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>ptions and ungrounded Confidences, of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> their deceitful and treacherous Hopes;
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:42338:52"/>and thoſe that ſtumble at the ſeandalous Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons that are in the Church, let them wait but a little, and theſe Spots ſhall be waſhed off from the Face; theſe Wens, theſe gan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>green'd Limbs ſhall be cut off from the Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy of the Church; this Droſs ſhall be p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> away for ever. Jeſus Chriſt hath a ſhaip Sickle to cut thoſe Tares, <hi>Rev.</hi> 14.14. An Ax to hew down thoſe barren Trees. a Fan to purge his Floor, a Furnace <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> unquenchable Fire to burn up the Chaff <hi>Matth.</hi> 3.12. The Goats and the Sheep go in the ſame Paſture in the Day-time, b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> when the Evening comes, there is a Separa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; the Goats go to their Penn, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e Sheep to their Fold: So Jeſus Chriſt, when he comes to judge the World, ſhall ſeparate the Goats and Sheep, <hi>Matth.</hi> 25.31, 32 Though they are now in the ſame viſible Church, yet Jeſus Chriſt ſhall part them, and ſet the Sheep on his Right-hand, and the Go<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> on his Left. Chriſt will diſown Hypocrites and exclude them out of his Glory: He wil<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> own the Sincere, and call them to inherit <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> Kingdom, <hi>Matth.</hi> 25.34. Do not raſhly judge thoſe to be related to Chriſt, that will be rejected by him. They that Feign, that Flatter, that Lye to Joſus Chriſt, will be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tected and abhorred by him; his Eyes wil be as a flaming Fire to diſcover them, and his Wrath will be as a conſuming Fire to bum them up. But then the true Church of
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:42338:52"/>Chriſt ſhall be as a Bride adorned for her Husband, <hi>Revel.</hi> 21.2. She ſhall ſhine with beautiful Holineſs, and glorious Righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, and be without ſpot and wrinkle, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 5.25, 26, 27. mete to be preſented and fit to be married to Chriſt, and to be an Object of his Love for Chriſt to rejoice in, and delight himſelf with to Eternity. Then ſhall there be no more a pricking Briar, a wounding or piercing Thorn, no ſtink<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Weeds, no empty Vines, no barren Fig-Trees in the Garden of God. Nothing ſhall any longer deſorm, or defile the Church. The People of the Church ſhall be all righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, the Branch of God's planting, the Work of his Hands, that he may be glorified, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 60.21. The Image of God ſhall be fully drawn on them, the Law of God ſhall be perfectly tranſcribed into them, no Fooeſteps of Sin ſhall remain on them, no droſs of Corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion ſhall cleave to them; they ſhall be tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed by the perfect renewing of their Minds: Then they will appear as Trees of Righteouſneſs, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 61.3. and bear all plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſant Fruits, and the chief of Spices, <hi>Cant.</hi> 4.13, 14. And thoſe that have flouriſh'd in God's Nurſery below for a time, they ſhall at laſt be tranſplanted into, and ſo grow in the Heavenly Paradiſe for ever.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="publishers_advertisement">
            <pb facs="tcp:42338:53"/>
            <head>Advertiſement.</head>
            <head type="sub">Theſe BOOKS are Publiſhed the Author of this Book.</head>
            <p n="1">1. THE Great Duty of Chriſti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> to go forth without the Ca<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> to <hi>Jeſus:</hi> Set forth in ſeveral Serm<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> on <hi>Hebr.</hi> 13.13.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Supplication to the Sovere<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Judge: The Duty of the beſt M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Set forth in ſeveral Sermons <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Job.</hi> 9.15.</p>
            <p n="3">3. A Diſcourſe in ſeveral Serm<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> on the 1 <hi>Peter</hi> 3.19. <hi>By which alſo went and preached unto the Spirits Priſon.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
